<TEI><text><body>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1"><head>BOOK ONE</head>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
   
   <pb n="1"/>
   
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p>
      <pb n="1"/>
      Dareios and Parysatis had two sons, the elder Artaxerxes, the younger Cyros. When Dareios was ill and expected to die, he wished both his sons to be present.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
   <p>
      <pb n="2"/>
      The elder was there, as it happened, but Cyros had to be sent for from the province where he was governor and general-in-chief over all the troops that are stationed in the plain of the Castolos. Cyros then came up to the capital, taking with him Tissaphernes as his friend, and he brought up 300 men-at-arms of the Hellenic mercenaries under their captain Xenias, a Parrhasian.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
   <p>
      But when Dareios died and Artaxerxes succeeded, Tissaphernes slandered Cyros to his brother and said he was plotting against him. The king believed him, and seized Cyros to put him to death, but his mother begged him off and sent him back to his province.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
   <p>
      When Cyros got clear of this danger and disgrace, he determined never again to be in his brother’s power, but to make himself king instead, if he could. Cyros had his mother behind him to begin with, for she loved him more than the reigning Artaxerxes.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
   <p>
      Whenever anyone came to Cyros from the court, he treated them all so well that they went away friends to him rather than to the king. And the native troops he had he carefully trained to take the field, and made them loyal to himself.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
   <p>
      <pb n="3"/>
      Hellenic mercenaries again he assembled in as great force as possible, secretly, in order to keep the king quite unprepared. This is how he collected them. He sent word to the governors of all the garrisons he had in various cities, to enlist as many Peloponnesians as they could find, and the best, pretending that Tissaphernes was plotting against the cities. For in fact the Ionian colonies had belonged to Tissaphernes originally, being given him by the king; but then they had gone over to Cyros, all except Miletos.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
   <p>
      In Miletos, however, Tissaphernes had got wind beforehand that the people were going to do the same, and revolt to Cyros, and he had killed some and banished others. Cyros gave refuge to the banished men, and collected an army, and laid siege to Miletos by land and sea, and tried to restore the banished: this was another excuse for him to assemble his army.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
   <p>
      He sent also to the king, and asked him as his brother to give him those cities rather than let Tissaphernes rule over them; and his mother worked to help him. Thus the king did not see the plot against himself, but he thought that war with Tissaphernes was why he spent so much money on the army. He did not worry about fighting between Cyros and Tissaphernes, especially as Cyros was careful to send in the proper tribute from the cities that Tissaphernes had in his province.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
   <p>
      <pb n="4"/>
      Another army was being collected for him in the Chersonese, opposite Abydos, in the following manner. Clearchos was a Lacedaimonian exile; Cyros met him, admired him, and gave him 10,000 darics. <note>A Persian gold coin weighing about 128 grains.</note> Using this money to collect a force, he made war, with the Chersonese as his base, upon the Thracians who are settled farther up above the Hellespont, and since he thus helped the Hellenes, the Hellenic cities willingly contributed to the support of his men. In such way this army again was being secretly kept for Cyros.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
   <p>
      Besides, Aristippos the Thessalian was his friend; and he, being hard pressed by the opposing party at home, came to Cyros and asked him to provide three months’ pay for 2,000 men, which he thought would be enough to get the better of his rivals. Cyros gave him six months’ pay for 4,000, and requested him not to make friends with his rivals without consulting him. There again was an army in Thessaly being kept ready unnoticed.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
   <p>
      Proxenos the Boeotian was another friend; Cyros begged him to get as many men as he could and join him, since he was about to attack the Pisidians who were making themselves a nuisance to his country. Two other friends, Sophainetos the Stymphalian and Socrates the Achaian, he told to join him with as large forces as possible, because he was going to make war on Tissaphernes along with the Milesian exiles. And so they did.
   </p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         When he thought the time had come to march up country, he made the excuse that he wanted to expel the Pisidians from the land altogether; and he summoned both his national forces and the Hellenic to meet for this purpose.
         <milestone unit="para"/>
         He also sent word to Clearchos to bring up all his army; and to Aristippos, to make terms with his rivals at home and to send the whole army to himself. He ordered Xenias also, who was in general command of the foreign troops in the cities, to bring them all up except as many as were enough to garrison the fortresses, 
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>       
         and except those who were besieging Miletos; the exiles he told to come too, promising them that if he should succeed in his purpose, he would not cease until he could restore them to their home. They obeyed gladly, for they trusted him, and proceeded to Sardis under arms.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>
         Accordingly Xenias came also to Sardis with about 4,000 men-at-arms; Proxenos was there with 1,500 and 500 light-armed men, Sophainetos the Stymphalian with 1,000 men-at-arms, Socrates the Achaian with about 500, Pasion the Megarian with 300 men-at-arms and 300 targeteers; he and Socrates had been among those besieging Miletos.     </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>This was the force that assembled at Sardis; Tissaphernes took note of this, and thought it was too large for the Pisidians, and so he marched to the king as quickly as possible with 500 horse. And the king made preparations to resist Cyros’s plan, when he heard about it from Tissaphernes.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         Cyros then, with the forces I have mentioned, set out from Sardis. Three stages, 22 leagues, <note>The parasang was a little over three miles. The plethron is about 100 feet. The men-at-arms are hoplites in heavy armour, the targeteers peltasts with light shields, light troops.</note> brought him as far as the River Maiandros. The river is 200 feet wide, with a bridge supported on floating vessels.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
 Crossing this, he travelled through Phrygia, one stage, 8 leagues, to Colossai, an inhabited city, large and prosperous. There he stayed seven days; and there Menon the Thessalian joined him, with 1,000 men-at-arms and 500 targeteers, Dolopians and Ainanians and Olynthians.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         Thence he passed on three stages, 20 leagues, to Celainai, an inhabited city of Phrygia, large and prosperous. There Cyros had a palace, and a great park full of wild animals, which he used to hunt on horseback when he wished to exercise himself and his horses. Through this park flows the River Maiandros, and the source is in the palace; it flows also through the city of Celainai.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
         There is also a palace of the Great King in Celainai, deserted, at the source of the River Marsyas under the Acropolis; this river also flows through the city and discharges into the Maiandros. The width of the Marsyas is 25 feet. There it is said Apollo flayed Marsyas, <note>Marsyas the satyr picked up Athena's hoboy, which she threw away because it made her look ugly to blow it; and he was so pleased with himself that he challenged Apollo to a match.</note> who had challenged him to a music-match, and hung up the skin in the cave where the source is; and therefore the river is named Marsyas.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         This palace and the fortress Xerxes is said to have built when he came back after the defeat in Greece. There Cyros remained thirty days; and Clearchos the Lacedaimonian exile joined him, with 1,000 men-at-arms, and 800 Thracian targeteers, and 200 Cretan bowmen. At the same time Sosis the Syracusan came in with 300 men-at-arms, and Sophainetos with 1,000 from Arcadia. There Cyros held a review, and counted the Hellenic mercenaries in the park; there were in all 11,000 men-at-arms, and about 2,000 targeteers.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
         From this place he marched two stages, 10 leagues, to Peltai, an inhabited city, where he stayed three days. In this halt Xenias the Arcadian celebrated the feast Lycaia and held sports; the prizes were golden skin-scrapers, <note>used in the bath, and usually made of iron</note> and Cyros looked on at the contest.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>
         From this place he marched two stages, 10 leagues, to Potters’ Market, an inhabited city, on the boundary of Mysia. From there he marched three stages, 30 leagues, to the plain of the Caystros, an inhabited city, where he stayed five days. More than three months’ wages were now due to the soldiers, and they came often to his door to ask for it. He talked of expectations and put them off; but he was clearly annoyed, for it was not the way of Cyros, if he had, not to give.
      </p>
   </div>
  
  
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>
         At this place came to Cyros Epyaxa, wife of Syennesis, King of the Cilicians, and she was said to have given him large sums of money, so Cyros paid the army four months’ wages. The Cilician queen had a bodyguard of Cilicians and Aspendians; and Cyros was said to have been intimate with her.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
         Thence he marched two stages, 10 leagues, to Thymbrion, an inhabited city. There by the side of the road was the spring named after Midas the Phrygian king, where Midas was said to have caught the Satyr by mixing wine with the water.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
         Thence two stages, 10 leagues, to Tyriaion, an inhabited city, where he stayed three days. The Cilician is said to have begged him to show her a display of the army. So he reviewed his troops, national and Hellenic, on the plain.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>
         He ordered the Hellenes to put themselves in battle array after their own fashion, each captain commanding his own men. So they paraded four deep; Menon held the right wing and Clearchos the left, the others in the centre.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
      <p>
         First Cyros inspected the nationals; they marched past in troops of horse and companies of foot. Then the Hellenes, Cyros driving by in a car and the Cilician in her state wagon. All the men wore bronze helmets and purple tunics and greaves, and had their shields uncovered.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
      <p>
         When he had driven by them all, he halted his car in front of the central line and sent Pigres the interpreter to the Hellenic captains with the order to present pikes and advance the whole line. The captains passed on the order to the men; and when the trumpet sounded, they presented pikes and advanced. Then the pace quickened. The men doubled towards the tents with cheers of their own accord.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
      <p>
         There was a panic among the national troops, and the Cilician fled in her wagon, and the people from the market fled too, leaving their goods behind. The Cilician was amazed to see the brilliancy and discipline of the army; and Cyros was delighted when he saw how the natives were scared by the Hellenes.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
      <p>
         From this place he went three stages, 20 leagues, to Iconion, the last city of Phrygia, where he stayed three days. Thence he marched through Lycaonia five stages, 30 leagues. He gave this part over to the Hellenes to despoil as enemy country.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
      <p>
         After that Cyros sent the Cilician back to her own country the quickest way, and with her he sent Menon and his men. But Cyros marched along with the others through Cappadocia four stages, 25 leagues, to Dana, an inhabited city, large and prosperous, where they stayed three days. Here Cyros put to death a Persian, Megaphernes, one who wore the royal purple, <note>the highest rank, others wearing purple facings only</note> and another high official, one of the lieutenant-governors, on the charge of conspiracy against him.
      </p>
   </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
      <p>
         After that they tried to break into Cilicia; but the entry was a carriage road, very straight and impossible for an army to enter if anyone resisted. Syennesis was said to be on the heights guarding the pass, and Cyros therefore stayed one day in the plain. But next day news came that Syennesis had left the heights when he found that Menon’s force already was in Cilicia and behind the mountains, and that a fleet of war under Tamôs was sailing round to Cilicia from Ionia, a fleet that belonged to the Lacedaimonians and to Cyros himself.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
      <p>
         So Cyros came up that pass into the mountains without opposition, and saw the tents where the Cilicians had been on the watch. After that he came down into a large and beautiful plain well watered, and full of all sorts of trees and vines, bearing plenty of sesamum, too, and millet and barley and wheat; a strong and lofty wall of mountains surrounds it everywhere from sea to sea.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
      <p>
         Coming down he marched through this plain four stages, 25 leagues, to Tarsus, a city of Cilicia both large and prosperous, where was the palace of Syennesis, King of Cilicia; through the midst of the city flows a river called Cydnos, 200 feet across.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
      <p>
         The inhabitants, with Syennesis, had left it and gone to a strong place in the hills, except those who had goods for sale; those who lived by the sea also remained, and those in Soli and Issos.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
      <p>
         Epyaxa, the wife of Syennesis, had reached Tarsus five days before Cyros; but in crossing the mountains two companies of Menon’s force had been lost; some said they had been cut down by the Cilicians while plundering, others that they had been left behind and could not find their party, and lost their way and wandered about till they perished. In any case they were a hundred men-at-arms.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
      <p>
         When the others came in they were enraged at the destruction of their comrades, and plundered Tarsus and the palace there. When Cyros entered the place he summoned Syennesis; but Syennesis said he had never yet put himself in the hands of one stronger than himself, and he would not come to Cyros then, until his wife persuaded him and got promises of safety.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
      <p>
         After this, when they met, Syennesis gave Cyros large sums of money for his campaign, and Cyros gave him such gifts as are thought honourable for a king, a horse with golden bit and bridle, and a gold necklace and bracelets, and a gold scimitar and Persian robes, and promised no more to plunder the country; he should have back the captives whenever he found any.
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         There Cyros and the army stayed twenty days, for the soldiers said they would go no farther; they already suspected that they were marching against the king, and said they had not been hired for that.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>
Clearchos first tried to compel his men to go on; but they pelted him and his animals as soon as they started, and Clearchos had a narrow escape then of being stoned to death. But after he saw he could not compel them he called a public meeting of all the men. He began by standing before them for some time with tears running down his cheeks, and the men were silent in surprise; then he spoke as follows:
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
         “Men and comrades, don’t be surprised that I am deeply hurt by what has happened. Cyros has been my friend; when I was banished from my country, he treated me with respect, and also gave me ten thousand darics; and when I received this money I did not put it by as my own, or spend it on luxuries, but I spent it on you. 
              </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
Then first I made war on the Thracians, and with your help punished them for the wrongs of Hellas. I drove them from the Chersonese, where they wished to rob our countrymen of their land. Afterwards, when Cyros called me, I marched with you to him, that if he needed me I might show my gratitude for his benefits.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         “But since you will not march with me, I must of necessity either desert you and enjoy his friendship, or else deceive him and stay with you. If it will be right I do not know; but in any case I will choose you, and with you suffer whatever I must suffer. No-one shall ever say that I led Hellenes against savages, and then deserted the Hellenes and chose the friendship of savages;      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
but since you will not obey me, I will go with you and suffer whatever I must suffer. For I consider that you are my country and my friends and comrades; and with you I think I shall be honoured wherever I may be, but without you, I think I am not able either to help a friend or hurt an enemy. Where you go there I will go also: that is my resolve.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         So he spoke, and the soldiers all cheered him, both his own and the others who heard, when he said he would not march against the king; and more than two thousand from Xenias and Pasion took their arms and baggage and encamped beside Clearchos.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
         Cyros was very much upset and did not know what to do. He sent for Clearchos, but Clearchos did not wish to go himself; he sent him a message, however, unknown to the soldiers, and told him not to worry, all would turn out well; but he should go on sending for him, and he would refuse to come.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         After that Clearchos collected his own men, and those who had joined him, and anyone else who liked, and spoke to them after this fashion: “Men and comrades, it is clear now how things are between us and Cyros: we are no longer his men, since we do not follow him; and he no longer finds our pay.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
He thinks you are in the wrong, I know; and that is why I will not go when he sends for me. The chief reason is, I am ashamed because my conscience tells me I have broken faith with him altogether; next I am afraid that if he catches me he may punish me for the wrong he thinks I have done.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>
         “Then I think it is no time for us to sleep or neglect ourselves; we must make some plan. As long as we remain here I think we must arrange to be as safe as possible; or if we decide to go at once, we must arrange to go as safely as possible and to find provisions, for without this there’s no good in a captain and no good in a man.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
   <p>
      But this man is worth much as a friend, and very dangerous as an enemy: he has forces
      in foot and horse and fleet, which we all see and understand quite well. Indeed, I don’t
      think we should sit here any longer. So now’s the time to say what is best; speak up,
      someone.” He said this and ceased; 
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
   <p>
      and people got up, some of themselves to tell what they proposed,
      others prompted by him, who pointed out what a mess they were in without the
      support of Cyros, whether they stayed or marched.  </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
   <p>One indeed pretended he was in
      a hurry that they should march for Hellas as quickly as they could, and told them to
      choose captains with all expedition, if Clearchos did not want to lead them; provisions
      they must buy <note>(there was a market in the national army)</note> and pack up their traps; they must go
      and ask Cyros for ships to sail in; if he would not grant this, ask him for a guide to see
      they travelled among friends.

      If he would not give so much as a guide, they must put themselves in order at once
      and send men on ahead to occupy the heights, or else Cyros might get there first, or the
      Cilicians—don’t forget we have taken many of them and their goods. <milestone unit="para"/>
      After this speech Clearchos got up and said:
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
   <p>
      “Me to be captain of this march—let no-one say such a thing! I see many reasons
      why I cannot do that. But I will be ruled by the man you choose, whoever he may
      be, to show you I know how to obey as well as any man on earth!”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
   <p>
      After this another got up, and showed how silly the man was who advised them to
      ask Cyros for ships. Did they think he would turn his feet backwards? How silly to ask
      <pb n="11"/>
      for a guide from a man when we have just spoilt his business! And if we trust the guide
      he gives us, what hinders him from giving orders to occupy the heights first?    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
   <p>“I should
      be sorry myself to embark in any ships he might give. Suppose he sinks us and the
      ships! I should be afraid to follow the guide he might give. Suppose he leads us to a
      place we can’t get out from! I should wish to get away without his consent, unnoticed;
      and that is impossible.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
   <p>
      I tell you all this is nonsense. I propose that Clearchos go with suitable people, and
      ask what Cyros means to do with us; and if his business now is like what he did with
      other hired soldiers before, that we follow him too and show ourselves no worse than
      those whom he brought up country earlier;   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
   <p>
but if the business is bigger than the
      other, and more difficult and dangerous, demand that he either persuade us and we
      will go, or be persuaded and let us depart in friendship. In that way, if we follow him
      we shall be friends and follow willingly, and if we depart we shall depart safely. Let them
      report to us whatever he says; <milestone unit="para"/> he will listen and decide accordingly.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
   <p>
      This was agreed; they chose the persons and sent them with Clearchos, and they
      asked Cyros the questions which the army thought proper. He answered, that he heard
      an enemy of his, Abrocomas, was on the River Euphrates twelve stages away; he said
      he wanted to march against this man, and if he was there he wished to punish him, but
      if he were gone, <note>we will consider what to do.</note>
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
   <p>
      The chosen men reported this answer to the soldiers; they had a suspicion that he
      was leading them against the king, still all the same they decided to follow. But they
      asked more pay; and Cyros promised to pay them all half as much again as they had
      had before, instead of one daric, one and a half each month per man; but as to the
      king, no-one heard one single word about that, in public at least.
   </p>
   <pb n="12"/>
</div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>From that place he marched two stages, 10 leagues, to the
         River Pharos, which was 300 feet across. Thence one stage,
         5 leagues, to the River Pyramos, 1 furlong wide. Thence
         two stages, 15 leagues, to Issoi, the last inhabited city of Cilicia,
         lying by the seaside, a large and prosperous place, 
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>where
         they stayed three days.
         There the ships from the Peloponnese
         joined Cyros, thirty-five with a Lacedaimonian admiral,
         Pythagoras. Tamôs the Egyptian piloted them from
         Ephesos, and he brought five and twenty other ships belonging
         to Cyros, with which he had besieged Miletos while it
         was friendly to Tissaphernes and fought against him for
         Cyros.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
         A Lacedaimonian Cheirisophos was also in this fleet,
         sent for by Cyros; and he brought 700 men-at-arms, whose
         captain was on the side of Cyros. The ships were anchored
         opposite Cyros’s tent. There were also the Hellenic mercenaries
         from Abrocomas, 400 men-at-arms; they had left him
         and come over to Cyros for his expedition against the king.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>From that place he marched one stage, 5 leagues, to the
         Gates of Cilicia and Syria. These were two forts; the inner
         one, in front of Cilicia, was held by Syennesis and a Cilician
         garrison; the other one, in front of Syria, was said to be
         held by a king’s garrison. Between the two forts runs a river
         named Carsos, 100 feet wide. The whole distance between
         the two forts was 3 furlongs. No force could get through;
         for the pass was narrow, and the walls ran down to the
         sea, and above were high-clambering rocks: both fortresses
         had gates.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         Because of this pass Cyros had sent for the ships;
         he would land forces both within and without the gates, and
         fight his way through the enemy if they were protecting
         the Syrian Gates, which he expected Abrocomas to do with
         a large army. But Abrocomas did not do this: when he
         heard Cyros was in Cilicia, he left Phoenicia and marched
         to the king, with an army of 300,000 as it was reported.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
         From here Cyros marched through Syria one stage, 5
         leagues, to Myriandros, a city inhabited by Phoenicians beside
         the sea: the place was a port of trade, and a great many
         merchant ships were anchored there. In this place he stayed
         seven days.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         Here Xenias the Arcadian and Pasion the Megarian
         put their valuables aboard a ship and sailed off;
         being offended, as most people thought, because Cyros allowed Clearchos to keep the men who had deserted to
         Clearchos, when they meant to go back to Hellas and not
         against the king. When these two could not be found, word
         went about that Cyros was in pursuit with warships; some
         hoped the cowards would be caught, others pitied them if
         they should be caught. 
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
         But Cyros called a meeting of the
         captains and said: “Xenias and Pasion have left us. But be sure they have
         not deserted: I know where they have gone. Nor have they
         escaped: I have galleys to catch their boat. But by God I
         will not pursue them! No-one shall say that I use a man
         while he is with me, but if he wants to go I catch him and
         maltreat him and rob him of his goods. Let them go, and
         remember that they treat us worse than we treat them.

         Indeed I have their wives and children still, guarded in
         Tralles; but they shall not lose them. They shall have them
         again in return for their good service so far.”       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p><milestone unit="para"/>
         That was what he said. And when the Hellenes heard
         the fine spirit of Cyros, if anyone was rather discouraged
         about the enterprise, they went on more happily and more
         willingly.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>After this, Cyros marched four stages, 20 leagues, to the
         River Chalos, 100 feet wide, which was full of large tame
         fish, which the Syrians, revering as gods, would not let
         anyone hurt—or the pigeons either. The villages where
         they encamped belonged to Parysatis, given for the queen’s
         girdle.<note>like others, given her for such excuses as perquisites</note>       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>Thence he marched five stages, 30 leagues, to the
         source of the River Dardas, breadth 100 feet. There was the
         palace of Belesys, the ruler of Syria, and a park large and
         beautiful, which contains all the kindly fruits of the earth,
         But Cyros cut down the trees and burnt the palace.
         <pb n="14"/>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
   <p>
      From there, three stages, 15 leagues, to the Euphrates, half a mile in width; and a large prosperous town was there named Thapsacos, where he stayed five days.
      <milestone unit="para"/>
      Then Cyros assembled the Hellenic captains, and told them their road was to the Great King at Babylon; they were to inform the men and persuade them to follow.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
   <p>
      So they called a public meeting and informed them. The men were angry with their captains, and said they had known this all along and hidden it from them; said they would not march, unless they were paid as the former expedition had been which had marched up country with Cyros to the father of Cyros, and then not for battle but invited by the father of Cyros.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
   <p>
      This the captains reported to Cyros; and he promised to give each man five minas of silver when they reached Babylon, and pay in full until he should bring the Hellenes back to Ionia. Most of them agreed to this offer. But Menon mustered his own detachment apart, before it was clear what the other captains would do, and said to them:
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
   <p>
      “Men, listen to me. You will be able to win credit with Cyros above the others, without danger and without trouble.
      <milestone unit="para"/>
      Then what do I advise you to do? Now Cyros asks the Hellenes to follow him against the king: I say you ought to cross the Euphrates before it is clear what the others will answer. If they vote to follow, you will be thought to be the cause, by crossing first; Cyros will think you the most ready and willing, and he will thank you and prove his gratitude—he knows how to do that better than anyone.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
   <p>
      If they vote against, we shall all go back together, but you he will trust most as the only ones ready to obey, and he will put you in charge of garrisons or other commands;
      <pb n="15"/>
      whatever else you may want, I know you will find Cyros a friend.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
   <p>
      When they heard this, they complied, and went across before the others made any answer. Cyros was delighted when he heard they had crossed, and sent Glûs to tell them so: he said:
      <milestone unit="para"/>
      “I am pleased with you now, men, and I will take care you shall be pleased with me, or my name is no longer Cyros!”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
   <p>
      The soldiers were in high hopes, and prayed good fortune for him; it was said also that he sent magnificent gifts for Menon.
      <note>Menon figures in Plato as fond of money, and “the spoilt child of fortune."</note> Then Cyros crossed, and the whole army followed.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
   <p>
      In the crossing, no-one was wetted above the breast. The people of Thapsacos said that this river had never been fordable for foot soldiers before that; it could be crossed only by boats, and Abrocomas had burnt them all on his way past, that Cyros might not cross. This was believed to be a sign from heaven, and the river had plainly made way for Cyros as destined to be king.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
   <p>
      From that place he marched through Syria nine stages 50 leagues, as far as the River Araxes. Many villages were there, full of corn and wine; there they stayed three days and got provisions.
   </p>
</div>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         Thence he marched through Arabia, keeping the Euphrates
         on the right, five stages of desert, 35 leagues. In
         this part the country was one great flat plain like a sea, but
         covered with absinth; whatever there was besides of wood
         or reeds, all were sweet-smelling like spices.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>There was
         no tree, but all sorts of animals, troops of wild asses, plenty
         of ostriches, bustards also and gazelles; and the horsemen
         often chased these. The asses, if they were chased, ran ahead
         and stood still, for they ran much faster than horses. When
         the horses came near, they ran as before, and they
         could not be caught unless the horsemen placed themselves
         at intervals and hunted in relays. The meat of those caught
         was like venison but more tender.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
         No-one caught an ostrich; horsemen in chase soon gave up, for she got far away before
         them, running on her feet and flying too, using her wings
         like a sail. Bustards, however, can be caught if you put
         them up smartly, for they fly in short spurts like a partridge
         and quickly tire. Their flesh was very good.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
         Marching through this country they came to the River
         Mascas, width 100 feet. There was a great deserted city
         named Corsote; this was surrounded by the Mascas,        </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>and
         there they stayed three days and got provisions. From that
         place he marched thirteen desert stages, 90 leagues, keeping
         the Euphrates on his right, until he reached the Gates. In
         these stages many of the baggage-animals were starved to
         death, for there was neither grass nor any sort of tree, but
         the whole country was bare: the natives used to dig up
         grinding-stones beside the river and shape them, and these
         they took to Babylon and sold them there, and bought corn
         to feed themselves. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>Corn failed the army, and none could
         be bought except in the Lydian market which Cyros had
         in his national camp, four shekels for a capith of wheat
         or barley: the shekel is worth seven and a half Attic obols,
         and the capith is two Attic quarts.
         <note>The Attic drachma contained six obols; so 7.5 obols is 1.25 drachmas. The
         quart, or choinix, was a man’s daily allowance of corn, minimum.</note>
         So the men had to
         manage by eating meat. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>Some of the stages were very
         long, when he wished to get on to water or grass.
          Once indeed when there was a narrow way and deep
         mud, bad going for the carriages, Cyros took charge with
         the noblest and richest of his staff, and ordered Glûs and
         Pigres to take some of his nationals and get the carriages
         through.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
As they seemed to be lazy about it, he was angry,
         and told the noble Persians beside him to lend a hand with
         the wagons. Then could be seen something of his discipline.
          Each man of them threw off his purple robe where he stood,
         and away they went as one might run a race! Down the
         steep hill they went, in their costly tunics and embroidered
         breeches, and some with necklaces round their necks and
         bracelets on their arms; in this garb they jumped straight
         into the mud, and quicker than one could think possible
         they got the wagons clear.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         Take it in all, Cyros showed himself to be in earnest
         throughout the march, and wasted no time except where
         he had to sit still for vittling or some other necessity. For
         he thought that the quicker he came, the less prepared for
         the fight would the king be. And it was easy to see for any
         sensible man that the king’s empire might be strong in
         extent and population, but it was weak by the long distances
         between his scattered forces if war were made suddenly
         with speed.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         On the other side of the Euphrates in the desert was a
         city great and prosperous named Charmande; from this
         place the soldiers bought provisions, and they crossed on
         rafts in this way. They took the skins which they used to
         cover their tents and stuffed them with hay, then folded
         and sewed them up to keep the water from the hay. On
         these they crossed, and got their provisions, wine made
         from dates and millet corn, which was commonest in that
         country.
      </p>
   </div>


   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
   <p>
      There was some quarrel there between Menon’s soldiers
      and those of Clearchos, when Clearchos judged that one
      of Menon’s men was in the wrong and flogged him. Menon
      went and told his party; the men were displeased and very
      angry with Clearchos.   </p>
   </div>


   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
   <p>On the same day Clearchos had
      gone to the crossing place, and after inspecting the market
      there he rode back to his tent with a few followers through
      Menon’s camp. Cyros had not yet come, but he was on the
      way. One of Menon’s men splitting wood saw Clearchos
      riding past, and threw the axe at him. This man missed
      him, but another threw a stone, and another, then many with shouts and cries. 
   </p>
</div>
<pb n="18"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
   <p>
      Clearchos got away into his own
      camp, and at once called them to arms; he told his own
      men to lean their shields against their knees,<note>ready to receive cavalry</note> and himself
      with the Thracians and horsemen he had in the camp,
      more than forty but mostly Thracians, he rode for Menon’s
      division. These were astounded and so was Menon, and
      all ran for their arms, some standing still on the spot in
      dismay. </p>
</div>
<pb n="18"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
   <p>Proxenos happened to come in behind them with
      a company of his men-at-arms, and he went straight in
      between them and grounded arms, and begged Clearchos
      to desist. But Clearchos was angry to hear his danger lightly
      spoken of when he had hardly escaped being stoned to
      death, and told him to get out of the way.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
   <p>
      At this moment Cyros came up and asked what the
      matter was. At once he took his javelin in hand and galloped
      in with those of his bodyguard that he had with
      him and said:
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
   <p>
      “Now then, Clearchos and Proxenos and you others,
      you don’t know what you are doing. If you make a fight
      among yourselves, understand that you will cut me to
      pieces this very day, and yourselves very soon after me!
      For if anything goes wrong with us, these people you see
      round us here will all be worse enemies to us than the king’s
      army.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
   <p>
      Clearchos came to himself when he heard this; both
      parties desisted, and went back quietly to their own quarters.
   </p>
</div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      <milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>As they moved onwards from this place, tracks of horses appeared, and dung. There seemed to be traces of something like two thousand horses. They were going ahead and burning the grass and anything else that was useful.
 
      Orontas, a Persian who was there, himself one of the royal family, and said to be one of the best men in Persia in military matters, made a treacherous proposal.

      He had formerly been at war with Cyros but made it up.    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>Now he told Cyros that if he would give him a thousand horsemen, he would either lie in wait for this incinerating vanguard and kill the lot, or else bring in a good many and stop their incinerating, and he would take care that they should never be able to see Cyros’s army and take the news to the king.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Cyros thought this sounded like useful advice, and he told him to take a part from each of the commanders. So Orontas thought the horsemen were there ready for him, and wrote a letter to the king that he would come and bring with him as many horsemen as possible. 

      He must warn his own cavalry to receive him as a friend. In the letter were also reminders of their former friendship and trust. This letter he gave to a trusty man, as he thought; but the man took it and gave it to Cyros.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Cyros read it, and arrested Orontas, and summoned to his own tent seven of the noblest men about him, and directed the Hellenic captains to bring armed men and post them around his tent. They did so, and brought some three thousand men-at-arms.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      He invited Clearchos in to be one of the court, for he thought him to be the leading man among all the Hellenes, and this was the public opinion too. 
    </p>
    <p>
      Afterwards he told his friends how Cyros conducted the court-martial; for it was no secret.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
    <p>
      Cyros began in this way: “I have summoned you, my friends, that I may consult you what is right to do before God and man, and so I may do about Orontas, who is here.
    </p>
    <p>
      This man was first given me by my father to be my subject. Then under orders, as he said himself, from my brother, he made war against me when he held the fortress of Sardis; and I took up the challenge and made him decide to cease war against me, and we clasped hands.
    </p>
    <p>
      After that, is there any wrong I have done you, Orontas?” 
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
    <p>He said, “No.”
      Again Cyros asked. “Then I did you no wrong after that, as you admit yourself, but did you desert to the Mysians and damage my country as much as you could?” Orontas said, “Yes.”
    </p>
    <p>
      “Very well,” said Cyros; “when you found out your own weakness, did you take refuge at the altar of Artemis, and say you were sorry, and did I believe you, and did we both pledge loyalty and friendship together?” This also Orontas acknowledged.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
    <p>
      “Then what wrong have I done you now,” said Cyros, “that for the third time you have been discovered planning treachery against me?” Orontas said that he had suffered no wrong.
    </p>
    <p>
      Cyros asked: “Do you admit, then, that you have done wrong to me?” “I can’t help it,” said Orontas.
    </p>
    <p>
      Then Cyros asked again: “And could you ever become an enemy to my brother again, and a faithful friend to me?” He answered, “Even if I should, Cyros, you would never believe it.”
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
    <p>
      Then Cyros turned to the court and said, “That is what the man has done, you hear what he says. You speak first, Clearchos; what is your judgment?”
    </p>
    <p>
      Clearchos said, “My advice is to get rid of this man at once, that we need not be obliged to watch him, but we may have leisure from him to do our best for these willing helpers.”
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
    <p>
      He said the others agreed with this judgment. After this, he said, at the bidding of Cyros, all those present, including the man’s kinsmen, rose and took hold of the girdle of Orontas as a sign that he must die. Then he was led away by those whose duty it was.
    </p>
    <p>
      But those who did reverence to him before, did reverence then, when they saw him, although they knew he was being led away to death.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
    <p>
      He was taken into the tent of Artapates, the most trusty of all Cyros’s wand-bearers, but after that no one ever saw Orontas alive or dead, and no one who knew ever told how he died.
    </p>
    <p>
      People guessed all sorts of things, but no tomb of Orontas was ever seen.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p>
            From that place he marched through Babylonia three stages, 12 leagues.
            In the third stage Cyros held a review of Hellenes and national troops on the plain at midnight,
            for he thought the king would be there at the coming dawn with his army, to fight.
            He ordered Clearchos to lead the right wing, and Menon the Thessalian the left, and he arranged his own troops himself.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p>
            After the review, with the daylight, deserters came in from the Great King and reported to Cyros about the king’s army.
            Cyros invited the captains and other officers of the Hellenes and held council on how he should arrange the battle,
            offering this cheering advice.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
        <p>
            “Gentlemen,” he said, “not for want of men have I brought you here as my allies,
            but I believe you to be better and stronger than large numbers of my own countrymen, and that is why I did it.
            Show yourselves men, therefore, worthy of the freedom which you possess and which I envy.
            Be sure I would give all I have and many times over if I could get that freedom.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
        <p>
            But I understand what a contest you have before you, and I will tell you, that you may understand also.
            The numbers are enormous, and they will come on with loud shouts and cries; but if you can stand that,
            I am ashamed to think what kind of men you will find in this country.
            If you show yourselves men, and if all goes well with my part,
            I will arrange that any one of you who wishes to return home will be the envy of those he meets at home;
            but I think I shall persuade many of you to choose what I have here rather than what he will find at home.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
        <p>
            Then Gaulites, a Samian exile who was present and a true friend of Cyros, said,
            “Oh yes, Cyros, but some do say that you can promise great things now, because all this danger is threatening,
            but you will not remember if all goes well, so they say;
            some say that even if you do remember, with the best of will you cannot pay all you promise.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
        <p>
            Cyros listened and said, “Well, gentlemen, my father’s empire reaches southwards as far as where it is too hot for men to live,
            and northwards to where it is too cold; all between is under the governance of my brother’s friends.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
        <p>
            If we are victorious, I must make my friends masters of all this.
            So I have no fear that I may not have something to give to each of my friends;
            what I fear is that there may not be friends enough.
            And to each of you Hellenes, I will give a golden crown.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
        <p>
            On hearing this they were much more cheerful and eager themselves, and they reported it to the others.
            Besides the Hellenic captains, many others paid Cyros a visit, asking what they would get if they won,
            and he sent them all away satisfied.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
        <p>
            All that spoke with him begged him not to expose himself in the battle, but to take post behind themselves.
            At this crisis Clearchos asked him once, “Do you really think he'll fight with you, Cyros, your own brother?”
            “I’m sure he will,” said Cyros, “if he is really the son of Dareios and Parysatis, if he really is my brother—
            not without a battle shall I win this prize.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
        <p>
            At the review the numbers were: Hellenes, shields 10,400; targeteers 2,500; national troops with Cyros, 100,000,
            and scythe-bearing chariots about 20.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
        <p>
            The enemy were said to be 1,200,000, with 200 scythe-bearing chariots.
            There were 6,000 cavalry besides, under Artagerses; these again were posted before the king himself.
        </p>
    </div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
        <p>
            The royal army was commanded by four marshals or generals, each having 300,000 men under him—
            Abrocomas, Tissaphernes, Gobryas, and Arbaces.
            But of these not all were present in the battle, only 900,000 men and 150 scythe-bearing chariots;
            for Abrocomas came five days too late, having to march from Phoenicia.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
        <p>
            This was what the deserters reported to Cyros before the battle, and after the battle, those that were left
            of the enemy said the same.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
        <p>
            From this place Cyros marched one stage, 3 leagues, with the whole army in array both national and Hellenic,
            for he thought the king would fight on that day. 
            Halfway through that stage, a deep trench had been dug, five fathoms across, three fathoms deep.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
        <p>
            The trench extended inland for twelve leagues over the plain as far as the wall of Media.
            (Here are the canals bringing water from the River Tigris; there are four, 100 feet wide and very deep,
            and barges of corn ply upon them; they discharge into the Euphrates, and are one league apart, with bridges over them.)
            Along the Euphrates was a narrow path, 20 feet in width, between the river and the end of the trench.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
        <p>
            This trench the Great King had made for a defense when he learned that Cyros was coming.
            Cyros and his army now passed along this path, and so they came inside the trench.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
        <p>
            So on this day the king did not fight, but there were many tracks of men and horses retreating.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
        <p>
            Here Cyros called Silanos the Ambraciot seer and paid him 3,000 darics for his bet, because eleven days before
            he had declared at the sacrifice that the king would not fight within ten days, and Cyros said, 
            “Then he won’t fight at all if he does not fight within ten days; and if your words come true, I promise you ten talents.” 
            So he paid him the money then, because ten days were past.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
        <p>
            But since here at the trench the king did not try to hinder the passage of Cyros and his army, both Cyros and the others
            believed he had given up the thought of fighting; so the next day Cyros marched more carelessly.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
        <p>
            The day after, he was leading the way seated in his chariot, with a small body of men in front, while most of the army
            was in disorder, and the soldiers had left much of their heavy arms to be carried by wagons or pack animals.
        </p>
    </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            It was already about full-market time,<note>9 or 10 a.m.</note> and the stage where they were to rest was near, 
            when Pategyas, a trusty Persian from the staff of Cyros, suddenly appeared galloping on a sweating horse, 
            and shouted out straight to all he met, in Greek and Persian, that the king with a large army was coming prepared for battle.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p>
            Then there was great confusion. 
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            The Hellenes thought, and so did all, that they would be attacked on the spot in this disorder.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
        <p>
            Cyros leapt from his car and put on his corselet, and got on his horse, and took his lances in hand, 
            and sent word to all the rest to arm and take post every man.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            At once they fell in with all haste, Clearchos holding the right wing on the Euphrates River, Proxenos next, 
            and then the others, with Menon commanding the left wing of the Hellenic forces.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
        <p>
            Of the national troops, 1,000 Paphlagonian horsemen took stand by Clearchos on the right, 
            and the Hellenic targeteers; in the left wing, Ariaios, Cyros’s second-in-command, and the other nationals; 
         </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
        <p>
                   and Cyros with his 600 cavalry in the centre, all except Cyros being armed with corselets, thigh pieces, and helmets, 
            but Cyros went into battle with bare head—it is said that the Persians generally risk fighting with the head bare.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            All the horses wore protections on forehead and breast, and the horsemen had Hellenic swords.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            It was already midday, and the enemy had not appeared; but when afternoon came dust appeared like a white cloud, 
            and some time afterwards a sort of blackness spreading far over the plain. But when they came nearer, quickly there 
            were flashes of bronze and spears, and the lines were visible.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
        <p>
            Cavalry in white corselets were on the enemy’s left wing; Tissaphernes was said to be in command of these. 
            Next came wicker-shieldmen, next men-at-arms with wooden shields which reached to their feet—these were said to be Egyptians; 
            then more cavalry, bowmen too. All these were arranged by nations, each nation marching as a solid square of men.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
        <p>
            In front of all were the chariots, with large spaces between, those which are called scythe-bearers. 
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            They had the scythes sticking out sideways from the axle-trees and under the cars pointing downwards, to cut through any they met. 
            The notion was to drive at the companies of Hellenes and cut them through.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            When Cyros had warned them not to mind the shouts and cries of the barbarians, he made a mistake; 
            there was no shouting, but they came on in deep silence, quietly in step, and slowly.
        </p>
    </div>

     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            At this moment, Cyros, riding past with Pigres the interpreter and three or four others, shouted out to Clearchos
            to lead his lines against the enemy centre, because the king was there: “If we beat that,” he said, “we have won!”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
        <p>
            Clearchos eyed the mass in the middle, and learnt from Cyros that the king was outside in the Hellenic left 
            (for the king so much exceeded in numbers that with his centre he overlapped Cyros’s left); he still was unwilling 
            to break away the right wing from the river for fear he might be turned on both flanks, so he answered Cyros 
            that he would take care that all went well.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            At this crisis the Persian army was advancing evenly, but the Hellenic line was halted as the men kept coming up
            and forming. Cyros was riding some way off from his army, and looking keenly at each side, staring at the enemy
            and his own men.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
        <p>
            An Athenian, Xenophon, saw him and went out to him from the Hellenic line, and asked if he had any orders.
            Cyros drew rein, and told him to spread the news everywhere that the omens from the sacrifice were all favourable.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            As he was speaking, he heard a confused noise running through the ranks, and asked what the noise was. 
            The other said that the word of the day was being passed round for the second time. Cyros wondered who
            gave the word, and what it was.        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
        <p>
 He answered: “Zeus Saviour and Victory.” Cyros said, “I accept the omen, 
            so be it!” As he spoke he rode away to his own place.

            <milestone unit="para"/>
            The two lines were hardly six or seven hundred yards apart when the Hellenes began to chant the battle hymn 
            and moved against the enemy.         </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
        <p>Part of the line billowed out as they moved, and the slower part began to double up; 
            then all together broke into a ringing cheer, “Eleleu, eleleu!” and all charged at the double. Some say they also 
            beat the spears on the shields to scare the horses.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Before one shot reached them, the barbarians turned and fled. At once the Hellenes pursued with might and main,
            but shouted to each other, “Don’t run races! Keep your line!”         </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
        <p>The chariots ran away without drivers, some through 
            their own people, some through the Hellenes: these saw them coming, and gave them room. One man was caught as he 
            stood like someone dazed in the middle of a racecourse; even this fellow had no hurt, so they said, and not one other 
            Hellene was hurt in this battle, except one on the left wing, said to have been shot by an arrow.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Cyros was delighted when he saw the Hellenes victorious in their part and pursuing; he was greeted as king already 
            by those about him, but even so he was not induced to join the pursuit. He kept his own body of 600 horse in close order,
            and watched to see what the king would do. He knew of course that the king held the centre of the Persian army.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Indeed all the generals of these barbarian nations hold the centre when they command; they consider it to be safest
            when their force is on both sides, and if they need to send dispatches, the army knows in half the time.         </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
        <p>So the king
            was then holding the centre of his army, and still overlapping the left wing of Cyros. Since there was no enemy in
            front, and none against the troops drawn up before him, he wheeled round to encircle Cyros.
        </p>
    </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Then Cyros, fearing he might get behind and cut up the Hellenic force, charged at him; with his 600 he fell on 
            the troops posted in front of the king, and put the 6,000 men to flight, and it is said killed with his own hand 
            their commander Artagerses.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
        <p>
            When those were routed, Cyros’s 600 were broken up in the pursuit, except a very few left about him, hardly 
            more than his table-companions, as they were called.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Left with these, he caught sight of the king and the bodyguard round him; then he could hold himself no longer, 
            but charged at him, saying, “I see the man!” and struck him on the breast and wounded him through his corselet, 
            as the doctor Ctesias reports, who says he cured the wound.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            As he struck, someone struck Cyros with a lance violently under the eye; and there as they fought, the king and 
            Cyros and the others about each, how many fell of the king’s party Ctesias tells, for he was in attendance; and 
            Cyros himself was killed, and eight of the most noble about him lay dead over his body.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            It is said that Artapates, who was the most trusted of all his wandholders, when he saw Cyros fallen leaped off 
            his horse and threw himself on the body.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Some say the king told a man to cut his throat over the body, some that he killed himself with his own scimitar—he 
            had a golden scimitar, and he wore bracelets and armlets and the other ornaments of the noblest Persians; for he 
            was highly honoured by Cyros for loyalty and trustworthiness.
        </p>
    </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            So died Cyros; of all Persians that came after the first
            Cyros, the most royal and most worthy to be king, as all
            agree who are reputed to have known Cyros themselves.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p>
            To begin with, when he was still a boy, and being educated
            along with his brother and the other boys, he was considered
            best of them all in everything.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            For all the sons of the noblest Persians are educated at the king’s door; there one
            may learn many a lesson in good manners, but nothing ugly
            can be heard or seen there.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
        <p>
            They see and hear when honour is done to any by the king,
            and when others are disgraced; so from boyhood they learn
            both to rule and to be ruled.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            There Cyros was thought to be the most modest
            of all his agemates, obeying his elders better than his own
            inferiors did.
            Next, he was the greatest lover of horses, and knew best
            how to manage them; and in war-like accomplishments, in
            archery and casting the javelin, they judged him the most
            eager to learn and the most careful to practise.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Again when
            he was old enough, he was most fond of hunting, ay and most
            ready to face danger among wild beasts. When a bear charged
            him once he did not shrink, but grappled with her; he was
            dragged off his horse, and received wounds which left their
            scars on him, but killed her at last; and he richly
            rewarded the first man who came to help.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Then he was sent down country as governor of Lydia
            and great Phrygia and Cappadocia, and appointed commander-in-chief
            of all the forces which had to assemble in the plain
            of Castolos.
 
            In this the first thing he made clear was, that if ever he made a
            truce or bargain or promise he never broke it.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
        <p>
            Indeed the cities put into his care all trusted
            him, and the men trusted him; and if anyone was an
            enemy, truce once made he trusted that nothing would be
            done to him contrary to that truce.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Accordingly when he
            made war against Tissaphernes, all the cities willingly chose
            Cyros instead of Tissaphernes, except Miletos; and there
            the people feared him because he would not abandon their
            banished men.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
        <p>
            For he said, and he proved by his acts, that
            he never would abandon them when once he had become
            their friend, not even if they lost numbers and lost luck.
        </p>
    </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            If anyone did either evil or good to him, he tried to outdo
            them, and made that quite clear. Some said that his common
            prayer was, “May I live as long as I can go one
            better with friends and foes!”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
        <p>
            Indeed there was no man
            alive in our time who found so many others eager to grant
            him money and city and even their own bodies.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            To be sure, no-one could say that he allowed any to do harm or
            wrong and then laugh in his face; he punished quite without
            mercy, and you could often see by the highroads persons
            lacking feet or hands or eyes. 

            The result was that in
            Cyros’s province a man might travel fearlessly where he
            would, whether Hellene or Asiatic, and carry whatever
            suited him, so long as he did no wrong.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Moreover, those who were good men in war he rewarded
            notably, as all agreed. For example, he had a war against the
            Pisidians and Mysians.

            He took the field himself against
            these countries; and when he saw men ready to take risks,
            he made these governors of the places he conquered, and
            rewarded them besides,
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
        <p>
            and so these were seen to prosper
            exceedingly, and the cowards were thought fit to be their
            slaves.<milestone unit="para"/> 
            Therefore he found plenty of volunteers in any risk,
            when they thought Cyros would see.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
        <p>
            In justice and honesty, if anyone showed himself glad to
            display these virtues, he took good care to make these
            richer than those who were greedy for unjust advantage.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            All his dealings were just, indeed, but he was especially particular
            to have a real army. Thus the captains and officers
            from abroad who served him for pay understood that to
            serve Cyros well was worth more to them than so much a
            month.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
        <p>
            Besides this, if anyone did serve him well, he never
            left willing service unrewarded. Accordingly Cyros always
            found, as they said, the best men to carry out any enterprise.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            If he saw one a skilful and just administrator, who managed
            his district well and collected the revenues, he never
            deprived him but always added to his trust; so men worked
            willingly, and got wealth boldly, and never tried to hide
            from Cyros what they got.
 
             He showed himself not one to
            envy those who were openly rich, but hidden riches he tried
            to bring into use.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Friends again, if he made any and found
            them loyal, and judged them capable assistants in what he
            wanted to do, he treated well, no man better, as all agree.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
        <p>
            For just as he wanted friends to help in each undertaking,
            so he tried his best to help these friends in anything which
            he saw they wanted.
        </p>
    </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            More gifts were offered to him, I believe,
            than to any other man who ever lived, for many reasons;
            and no-one was ever more ready to distribute these
            among his friends, while he considered their tastes to see
            what each wanted most.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
        <p>
            When the gifts were meant for his person, whether in battle
            or just as finery, he used to say, “I can’t deck out my body
            in all this finery, but a man’s best finery is when his friends
            go fine.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            In great things it is no wonder he could outdo his generous
            friends, since he had greater power; but he took care
            to have the better of them in little attentions and graces,
            which appears to me more admirable still.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
        <p>
            When he received some specially good wine, he would often
            send a keg half full to a friend, with a message, “I haven't drunk
            such good wine for a long time, so I send you this. Please drink it
            up to-day with your best friends!”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
        <p>
            Often he would send half a goose or half a cake, and things like
            that, telling his bearer to say, “Cyros liked this, and he wants
            you to have a taste.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            When hay was hard to get and he had plenty himself because
            he had provided it, and there were many servants, he
            would send round to tell his friends to stuff the horses they
            rode with this, that they might not starve while they carried
            his friends about.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
        <p>
            If he ever went on progress and
            crowds came to see him, he would call up friends and talk
            seriously to them, to show whom he valued.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            So from all I hear, I judge that no-one has ever been better
            loved by Hellenes and Asiatics alike. Here is another
            proof. When Cyros was the king's slave, no-one ever left
            him for the king, only Orontas tried, and indeed the king
            himself found that the man he thought faithful to himself
            was a better friend to Cyros.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
        <p>
            But from the king, many did
            come away to Cyros after they became enemies, and those
            more over whom the king cared for most—they thought that
            with Cyros if they played their parts well they would receive
            a worthier return than with the king.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            A great proof again is what happened at the end of his life,
            to show that he was noble himself, and knew how to judge
            rightly the trusty and loyal and firm; for when he died all his
            friends and table companions died fighting over him, except
            Ariaios, who was posted on the left wing, as it happened,
            in command of the cavalry.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32">
        <p>
            When he perceived that
            Cyros was dead he escaped with all his command.
        </p>
    </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p>
            Then the head and right hand of Cyros were cut off. The king, pursuing, fell on Cyros’s camp; those with Ariaios
            did not stand, but escaped through their own camp to the stage-house where they had come from; the distance was
            said to be four leagues.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p>
            The king and his troops plundered the camp, and took a great spoil, including the Phocaian
            mistress of Cyros, famous as “the clever and beautiful.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
        <p>
            The Milesian, who was younger, was caught by the king’s
            men, but she slipt out of her robe, and escaped to a body of
            Hellenes who happened to be on guard among the baggage
            animals. They resisted the plunderers and killed many of
            them, and of themselves some were killed, too, yet they
            did not take flight, but they saved the woman and everything
            else that was in their charge, goods and men.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
        <p>
            At this time the king and the Hellenes were three or four
            miles apart, the Hellenes pursuing and believing they were
            victorious everywhere, the others plundering and believing
            they were victorious themselves.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
        <p>
            But when the Hellenes
            perceived that the king and his army were in their camp,
            and when the king heard from Tissaphernes that the Hellenes
            were victors on their part and far away in pursuit, at
            once the king collected his forces and put them in order.

            Clearchos called Proxenos, who was nearest, and consulted
            him whether they should send a party or all go back to
            defend the camp.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
        <p>
            Meanwhile the king showed himself advancing from the
            rear, as it seemed. The Hellenes turned and prepared to
            receive his attack on the spot, but the king did not approach
            them; he passed them by the way he had come, outside
            what had been their left wing, catching up those who had
            deserted to the Hellenes in the battle, and also Tissaphernes
            with his division.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
        <p>
            For Tissaphernes when they first met had
            not taken flight, but he rode along the river through the Hellenic
            targeteers; he killed none in passing through, but the
            Hellenes made room and struck at them and volleyed as
            they went. Episthenes of Amphipolis was in command,
            said to be a capable officer.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
        <p>
            Tissaphernes then got rather
            the worst of it but came out clear; he did not turn back,
            but went as far as to the Hellenic camp, and there found
            the king, when they put their forces together again and
            went on.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
        <p>
            When they came to the Hellenic left wing the
            Hellenes were afraid they might attack and surround them
            and cut them to pieces, and they decided to extend their
            line and put the river behind them.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
        <p>
            While they were discussing this, lo and behold the king
            passed them, and placed his line opposite them in the same
            position as he was in at the beginning of the battle. When
            the Hellenes saw them near, and drawn up opposite, they
            chanted the battle-hymn again and charged much more
            vigorously than before.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
        <p>
            Again the barbarians would not
            stand, but ran even sooner than before.
        </p>
    </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
        <p>
            The Hellenes pursued them as far as some village, and
            there they halted; for above the village was a mound, on
            which the king’s party rallied, only cavalry now, but they
            covered the mound so that no-one could see what happened.
             But they said they did see the royal standard, a golden
            eagle, stretched across a shield and held up on a pole.        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
        <p>
As
            soon as the Hellenes moved again the horsemen at once left
            the mound, not all together but in small parties; the mound
            became bare by degrees, and at last they were all gone.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
        <p>
            Clearchos did not take his army upon the mound, but halted
            them at the foot, and sent up Lycios the Syracusan and one
            other to report what there was on the other side.        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
        <p>
 Lycios
            rode up, and reported that they were all going as fast as
            they could.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
        <p>
            Just then the sun set, the Hellenes halted and ordered
            arms, and rested, wondering why Cyros was nowhere to
            be seen and no messages came from him; for they did not
            know he was dead, but they supposed he was in pursuit,
            or gone forward to occupy some place.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
        <p>
            They deliberated
            whether they should stay there and bring up the baggage,
            or go back to camp. They decided to go back, and they
            reached the tents about supper-time.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
        <p>
            This was the end of that day. They found most of their
            goods plundered, and all the food and drink gone; even the
            wagons loaded with barley and wine which Cyros had
            provided to distribute if the army were in special need (400
            wagons, it was said), even these the king’s army had
            spoiled.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
        <p>
            So most of the Hellenes had no dinner, and they
            had not had breakfast either; for the king appeared before
            the army was dismissed for breakfast. So they passed that
            night.
        </p>
    </div>
</div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="2">
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p>
            At daybreak the captains met. They were surprised that
            Cyros had neither appeared himself, nor sent someone to
            tell them what to do. They decided, therefore, to collect what
            they had, and to get under arms, and to go on till they
            found him.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
        <p>
            As they were just starting, at sunrise, up came
            Procles, the governor of Teuthrania, a man descended from
            Damaratos the Laconian, and with him Glûs, the son of
            Tamó. These told them that Cyros was dead, but Ariaios
            had escaped, and was with the other Asiatics in the stagehouse
            from which they marched on the day before; he said
            he would wait that day for them, if they would come, but
            on the morrow he was going back to Ionia, where he came
            from.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
        <p>
            When they heard this the captains were very much distressed,
            and so were the other Hellenes. Clearchos said,
            “If only Cyros were alive! But pray report to Ariaios, that
            we are victorious over the king, and, as you see, no-one is
            left here to fight us; if you had not come, we should be
            on the march against the king now. We say to Ariaios that
            if he will come here, we will place him on the royal throne;
            for the kingdom belongs to the conquerors.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
        <p>
            With these words he sent the messengers away, and with
            them Cheirisophos the Laconian and Menon the Thessalian;
            Menon himself wished it, for he was a guest-friend of
            Ariaios.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
        <p>
            So they went, and Clearchos remained. The army prepared
            food as well as they could, butchering the cattle and
            asses of the baggage train; they got wood by going a little
            in front of their lines, where they found plenty of arrows
            on the battlefield, which they had forced the deserters from
            the king to throw away, and the shields of wickerwork
            and Egyptian wooden shields. There were plenty of bucklers,
            too, and empty wagons which they could carry off.
            They used all these to boil the meat which they ate that
            day.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
        <p>
            It was already about full-market time when messengers
            came from the king, heralds of the country, and one Hellene
            among them, Phalinos, who happened to be with Tissaphernes
            and highly respected; for he claimed to be expert
            in tactics and fighting in arms.       </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
        <p>These came and summoned
            the captains, and said, “The king having killed Cyros and
            won the victory, commands the Hellenes to lay down their
            arms, and find at the king’s door what good they can.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
        <p>
            Such was the king’s message. The Hellenes were very
            angry, but Clearchos only said, “It is not for victors to lay
            down their arms.” Then to the other captains, “You, my
            fellow-captains, answer these gentlemen as you think fairest
            and best; I will be here in a moment,” for a servant had
            just called him to see the sacred parts which had been taken
            out from a victim which was being sacrificed.         </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
        <p>Then Cleanor
            the Arcadian, eldest of them, said they would die sooner
            than lay down their arms; and Proxenos the Theban said,
            “I wonder, Phalinos, whether the king speaks as conqueror
            or asks our arms as a friendly gift. If as conqueror, why
            does not he come and take them? If he wants us to yield
            them willingly, let him tell us what the soldiers will have
            left, if they make him a present of these?”
        </p>
    </div>



        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
        <p>
            Phalinos answered, “The king considers he is victor, since he has killed Cyros. For who is there who will challenge him for his empire? He considers that you also are his, because he holds you in the midst of his country, surrounded by impassable rivers, and he can bring against you such a multitude of men as you could not kill if you had the chance.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
        <p>
            Theopompos the Athenian followed and said, “My dear Phalinos, we have nothing good here, as you see, except arms and courage. While we keep our arms, we think we can use our courage; but if we give them up, we shall lose our lives too.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
        <p>
            Hearing this, Phalinos laughed, and said, “Why, you are quite a philosopher, young man, you speak neatly; but let me tell you that you are foolish if you think your courage can overcome the king’s power.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
        <p>
            A few others, it is reported, showed a little weakness, and said they had been faithful to Cyros, and the king might find them valuable if he liked to be their friend; he might use them for a campaign into Egypt or something else, and they would go.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
        <p>
            At this moment Clearchos returned and asked whether they had given their answer. Phalinos broke in, and said, “These people say all sorts of things, Clearchos; tell us what you say.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
        <p>
            He answered, “I was glad to see you, Phalinos, and so were the others, I think; you are a Hellene, and so are we, every one of us that you see before you. In our present case we ask your advice as to what we ought to do.        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
        <p>Advise us in God’s name what you think fairest and best, something that will do you honour when it is reported in time to come: how Phalinos was once sent by the king to command Hellenes to lay down their arms, and they asked his advice, and this was his advice. You know it is inevitable, that whatever you advise will be told all over Hellas.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
        <p>
            Clearchos gave these hints hoping that the king’s ambassador might advise them himself not to lay down their arms, and then the others would be more confident. But Phalinos did the opposite; he turned round, and said,        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
        <p>“This is my advice. If you have one hope in ten thousand to make war against the king, and to save your lives, do not lay down your arms. But if there is no hope whatever of safety against the king’s wish, I advise you to save yourselves in the one way you can.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
        <p>
            Clearchos answered to this, “Very well, that is what you say: from us take this answer. We believe that if we are to be friends to the king, we should be more valuable friends with arms than without; and if we are to make war, it is better to make war with arms than without.”
        </p>
    </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
        <p>
            Phalinos said, “We will take back this answer; let me say that the king added, that there shall be a truce if you stay where you are, but if you move forwards or move backwards, war. Answer this too, then: will you stay, and is there a truce? Or shall I report that there is war?”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
        <p>
            Clearchos said, “Report then, that our view is the same as the king’s.” “What does that mean?” said Phalinos.
 
            Clearchos answered, “If we stay where we are, a truce; if we move forwards or backwards, war.”        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
        <p>He asked again, “Truce or war, which?” Clearchos made the same answer again, “Truce if we stay here, war if we move forwards or backwards.” But he did not indicate which he meant to do.
        </p>
    </div>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p>
            So Phalinos departed and those with him. Then Procles and Cheirisophos returned from Ariaios, but Menon stayed with him. These reported that Ariaios said there were many Persians better than himself who would never let him be king; “but if you wish to go away with him, he tells you to come to-night. Otherwise, he says he will go early in the morning.” 
                    </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p>
        Clearchos said, “Very good, so be it. If we come, then as you say; if not, do whatever you think most profitable for yourselves.” But he did not tell these either what he meant to do.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
        <p>
            After this, when the sun was already sinking, he called the captains and other officers together, and spoke to them. “Gentlemen,” he said, “I sacrifice for advance against the king, and the omens were not favourable. There is perhaps nothing strange in that; for between us and the king is the Tigris, a navigable river which we could not cross without boats, and boats we have none. However, we cannot stay where we are, for we cannot get provisions. But for going to the friends of Cyros the omens were completely favourable.         </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
        <p>This is what we must do. Dismiss, and dine on what we can find: when the first horn sounds for turning in, pack up; at the second, put the stuff on the animals; at the third, follow your guide, keeping the animals next to the river, and the shields outside.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
        <p>
            The captains and officers did so; and for the rest, he led and they followed—not that they chose him, but they saw that he alone understood what the leader ought to do, and the others were inexperienced.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
        <p>
            After this, when darkness came, Miltocythes the Thracian deserted to the king, taking with him his horsemen, forty in number, and some three hundred of the Thracian footmen.       </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
        <p>Clearchos led the others as he had told them, and they followed, and they reached Ariaios and his force at the first stage-house, about midnight. They grounded arms in their ranks; and there was a meeting of the captains and other officers with Ariaios.      The Hellenes and Ariaios and the chief of those with him swore to be allies and to be faithful to one another; the nationals also swore to lead the way honestly.  </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
        <p>This they swore, cutting the throats of a bull and a boar and a ram over a shield: the Hellenes dipt a sword in the blood, the Asiatics a spear.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
        <p>
            When the oath had been taken, Clearchos said: “Now then, Ariaios, since the same journey is before us all, tell me what notion you have of the road. Are we to return the same way as we came, or have you thought of another that seems better?”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
        <p>
            He said, “If we go back by the way we came, we should perish of hunger outright; for we have no provisions now. Even on our way here we got nothing at all from the country on the seventeen last stages; where there was anything we have used it all up on the march already. The way we think of taking now is longer, but there will be no lack of provisions.”
        </p>
    </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
        <p>
            We must make the first stages as long as we can, that we may get away from the royal army as far as we can; for if once we can put two or three days’ journey between us, the king will never be able to catch us. With a small force he will not dare to follow; with a large force he will not be able to go fast, perhaps he will even fall short of provisions. That’s my opinion,” he said.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
        <p>
            This plan of campaign meant nothing more than to cut and run; but fortune planned better.
             When day came, they marched with the sun on their right hand, calculating that by sunset they would reach villages in the Babylonian country; and in this they were not deceived.        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
        <p>
But while it was still afternoon they thought they saw enemy horsemen; and those of the Hellenes who were not in their ranks fell in, and Ariaios (who was travelling in a wagon because he had been wounded) got down and put on his corselet, and so did those with him.        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
        <p>
While they were arming, their scouts came back reporting they were not cavalrymen but pack-animals grazing. And they soon understood that the king was encamped somewhere near, for smoke was seen in villages not far off.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
        <p>
            Clearchos did not lead against the enemy, for he knew that the men were weary and hungry, and it was late already; yet he kept straight on without swerving, for he would not let them think he was running away, and at sunset he brought up his van to the nearest villages and encamped. From these everything had been stript by the royal army, down to the woodwork of the cottages.        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
        <p>
However, the first men encamped after a fashion, and those behind coming along in the dark lay in the open as it chanced, and they made a great noise calling to one another, so that even the enemy heard; and the nearest of the enemy even fled out of their encampment.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
        <p>
            This became clear next day; for not an animal was to be seen, no camp, no smoke anywhere near. The king himself was frightened, as it seemed, at the army’s approach, as he made clear by what he did the day after.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
        <p>
            However, as the night went on a panic fell on the Hellenes also and there was din and disturbance as one might expect in a panic.        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
        <p>
Clearchos sent round Tolmides the Elean, the herald who was with him as it happened, the best herald of his time; he was to call for silence, and proclaim from headquarters, one talent reward for information who let the ass loose in the camp.        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
        <p>
When this was proclaimed, the men knew that it was an empty panic and the commanders were safe and sound. At break of day Clearchos ordered the Hellenes to form in line in the same position which they had in the battle.
        </p>
    </div>

</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p>
            It was clear now that the king had been terrified by their approach, as I wrote above; for the day before he had commanded them to lay down their arms, but now at sunrise he sent heralds to treat for a truce.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p>
            When they reached the outposts, these went in search of their commanders; and Clearchos, who happened to be then reviewing the lines, heard the report of the outposts, and sent back word that the heralds were to wait until he had leisure.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
        <p>
            When he had arranged his army so that a solid array could be easily seen everywhere, with no-one visible outside the forces, he summoned the mission, and went to meet them with the best-armed and finest men he had, and told the other captains to do the same.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
        <p>
            When he came up to the mission, he asked what they wanted. They answered that they came to arrange a truce, with full powers from the king to treat with the Hellenes, and to report their proposals to the king.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
        <p>
            Clearchos then said, “Report to him, then, that first there must be battle; we have no breakfast, and no man shall dare to speak of truce to Hellenes without providing breakfast.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
        <p>
            When the embassy heard this, they rode away, and soon came back; so it was plain that the king was somewhere near, or someone whose duty it was to arrange things. They said that the king thought it a reasonable request, and they had brought guides to take them where they would find breakfast, if they could arrange a truce.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
        <p>
            Clearchos asked whether the truce was offered just for the men as they went and came back, or was it a general truce for all. They replied, “For all, until we give our report to the king.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
        <p>
            When they had finished, Clearchos removed them and held council; and it seemed best to accept this truce and quietly to go and get the provisions.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
        <p>
            So he said, “I agree with that, but I will not tell them at once; I will delay until the ambassadors are anxious for fear we may refuse to make truce. I think, however,” he said, “that our own men will fear the same!”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
        <p>
            When he thought it was the right time, he announced that he would make truce, and bade them lead him at once to the provisions. So they did; but Clearchos, although he had made the truce, marched with the army in battle order, himself commanding the rearguard. They came on ditches and canals full of water, which they could not cross without bridges; but they managed by making bridges of fallen date-palms or others which they cut down. 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
        <p>
            Then one could learn what a commander Clearchos was. In his left hand he held the spear, a stick in his right; and if he thought there was any shirking, he picked out the right man and gave him one, and also he lent a hand himself, jumping into the mud, so that all were ashamed not to work as hard as he did.
        </p>
    </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
        <p>
            Those of thirty years and under were told off for this job; but when they saw how keen Clearchos was, the older men helped.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
        <p>
            What made him more anxious was that he suspected the ditches were not always so full of water, for it was not the season for watering the plain; he thought the king might have let in this water on purpose to show them how many dangers they would meet on the march.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
        <p>
            At last they reached villages from which the guides directed them to take the provisions. There was plenty of corn and date-wine and a sour drink made by boiling dates.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
        <p>
            The palm-nuts or date-nuts which we see in our country are such as were kept for servants; but those reserved for the masters were select, wonderfully fine and large, just like amber in colour: and some they dry and store for delicacies. These were delicious as a relish for wine, but they give headache.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
        <p>
            That was the first time the men tasted the brain or top-cabbage of the palm, and most of them were surprised at the shape and peculiar flavour. This also was very apt to give headache. When the brain was taken from the palm, the whole tree withered.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>There they remained three days. Then arrived Tissaphernes, and the queen’s brother, and three other Persians, with a long train of slaves. When the Hellenic captains met them, Tissaphernes first spoke through an interpreter. He said:
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
        <p>
            “I am a near neighbour to Hellas, gentlemen; and when I saw you follow into danger and difficulty, I thought it a grand opportunity if I could persuade the king as a favour to let me bring you back safe to Hellas; for I think that would earn me your thanks and your country’s.        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
        <p>With this intention I put my petition before the king, saying that he might fairly gratify me because I first told him that Cyros was advancing against him, and I brought him aid along with my news; and I alone of all those who faced the Hellenes did not take to flight, but I rode through and joined the king in your camp which he had then reached, after killing Cyros and pursuing the nationals with Cyros along with the forces which are with me now, the most loyal of all his men. He promised me that he would consider this; 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
        <p>but he told me to come and ask why you made war upon him.
            And I advise you to answer moderately that it may be easier for me to find how I may arrange something good for you.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
        <p>
            The Hellenes retired and consulted what to say; and they answered, Clearchos being spokesman:
        
            “We did not assemble to make war on the king, nor did we march against the king; but Cyros found many excuses, as you know well yourself, that he might catch you unprepared and bring us here. </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
        <p>However, when we saw him in danger, we were really ashamed before gods and men to desert him, after offering ourselves to him long since for his service. </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
        <p>But now that Cyros is dead, we do not lay claim to the king’s empire, and there is no reason why we should damage the king’s country or wish to kill the king himself.
        
            We wish to march home, if no-one molests us; but if we are injured we shall try to defend ourselves, with God’s help. If moreover, anyone turns up to help us, we shall be no less ready to help him as far as we can.”
        </p>
    </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
        <p>
            Tissaphernes listened to him, and said, “I will report this to the king, and bring back his answer. Until I return let the truce be kept, and I will provide you a market.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
        <p>
            Next day he did not return, and the Hellenes were anxious; but he came the day after, and said he had procured from the king the boon of safety for the Hellenes, although many had urged that it was unworthy for the king to let go those who had made war against him.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
        <p>
            At the end he said, “Now you may receive our promise to keep the country at peace with you, and to take you back to Hellas without fraud; we will provide a market, and wherever you cannot buy, we will allow you to take what is necessary from the country.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
        <p>
            “You on your part must take your oath to march as through a friendly country, only taking food and drink without violence whenever we do not provide a market, but when we do you must buy provisions.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
        <p>
            This was agreed; they took the oath, and Tissaphernes and the queen’s brother gave their right hands to the captains and officers of the Hellenes, and these did the like.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
        <p>
            After this Tissaphernes said, “Now, then, I return to the king; when I have arranged what I wish, I will come back ready to conduct you to Hellas, and myself to return to my province.”
        </p>
    </div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p>
            After this the Hellenes and Ariaios waited for Tissaphernes, encamped near each other, for more than twenty days.
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Meanwhile Ariaios was visited by brothers and other relations, and some of his people had visits from Persians, who encouraged them, and brought pledges to some from the king, that the king would bear no malice against them for their campaign with Cyros or for anything else now bygone.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p>
            While this went on Ariaios’s people clearly began to think less about the Hellenes. So for this reason they displeased many of the Hellenes; and these complained to Clearchos and the other captains, and said:
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
        <p>
            “What are we waiting for? Don’t we know that the king would give anything to destroy us, and show our whole nation what a terror it is to make war on the Great King? Now he deludes us to stay because his army is scattered; but when the whole army is assembled again there is no doubt he will attack us.
                  </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
        <p>Perhaps they are digging somewhere or fortifying somewhere to make the road impassable. He will never be willing, if he can help it, that we shall go back to Hellas and report that a few men like us beat the king in front of his own door, and got away to laugh at him.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
        <p>
            Clearchos answered, “I have all this in my own mind, but I remember that if we go now he will think we have broken the truce and gone out for war. Then again, firstly no-one will make us a market or help us to get provisions; secondly, there will be no-one to guide us; thirdly, if we do anything like that Ariaios will leave us at once. So we shall not have one friend left, and even those who were friends will be our enemies.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
        <p>
            Then the river: if there is any other difficult river for us I don’t know, but the Euphrates we know cannot be crossed if the enemy oppose.
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            Further, we have no cavalry to help us if we must fight, but the enemy have plenty, and very good; so if we win, how could we kill anyone? And if we are beaten, none of us could escape.       </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
        <p>As for the king, with all these things in his favour, if he really wishes to destroy us, I don’t know why we need swear oaths and give pledges, and then by perjury make his own word worthless to all the world, both ours and his!” He would often speak like this.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
        <p>
            Meanwhile Tissaphernes came with his forces, as on the road home, and Orontas came with his; he brought also the king’s daughter, his bride.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
        <p>
            They left the place at once, Tissaphernes leading and providing a market; Ariaios marched also at the head of Cyros’s national force, along with Tissaphernes and Orontas, and camped with them.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
        <p>
            But the Hellenes suspected these, and kept to themselves with their own guides. They always camped with a distance between them, a league or more; both parties watched each other like enemies, and this at once made more suspicion.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
        <p>
            Sometimes when they were gathering wood from the same place, and foraging for grass and such things, they came to blows with each other, and this made more hostility.
        </p>
    </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
        <p>
            After they had gone three stages they reached what is called the Wall of Media, and passed behind it. This was 
            <pb n="46"/> 
            built of baked bricks set in asphalt, twenty feet thick, one hundred high; its length was said to be twenty leagues, and it is not far from Babylon.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
        <p>
            From this place they marched two stages, 8 leagues; and they crossed two canals, one by a bridge, one by eight boats fastened together. These canals came from the River Tigris; trenches are dug from them over the land, the first larger, then smaller ones, until at last they become little runnels such as we have in Hellas over millet fields.
            Then they reached the Tigris, near which was a city, large and populous, named Sittace, distant from the river about a mile and a half. 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
        <p>The Hellenes encamped near it beside a park, large and beautiful and thick with all sorts of trees; but the nationals crossed the river first, where they were quite hidden from view.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
        <p>
            After dinner it happened that Proxenos and Xenophon were walking in front of the camp, and a man asked the sentries where he could see Proxenos or Clearchos; he did not ask for Menon, although he came from Ariaios, Menon’s friend. 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
        <p>When Proxenos said, “I’m the man you are looking for,” the fellow said, “I have been sent by Ariaios and Artaozos, who were true to Cyros and remain loyal to you. 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
        <p>They bid you be on your guard against an attack to-night; there is quite an army close by in the park. And they bid you to send a guard for the Tigris bridge, because Tissaphernes intends to break it down to-night that you may not cross but may be caught between the river and the canal.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
        <p>
            Hearing this they took him to Clearchos, and told him what he said. Clearchos was very much upset and alarmed.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
        <p>
            But a young man present observed that the attack and breaking down the bridge did not fit well together. “If they attack,” he said, “they must either win or lose. If they win, why break down the bridge? For then we could never escape and be safe however many bridges there are. 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
        <p>But if we win, with a broken bridge they will never escape 
            <pb n="47"/> 
            themselves; nor will any of that multitude across the river be able to help them with a broken bridge.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
        <p>
            Clearchos listened, and asked the messenger how much country there was between the Tigris and the canal. He said a great deal, and many villages and many large cities. 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
        <p>Then he understood at once that the Persians had sent the man, for fear the Hellenes might cut the bridge and stay in the island, defended by the Tigris on one side and the canal on the other, and might get their provisions from the country between, which was large and good with plenty of hands to till it; then again, it might be a refuge for anyone who wanted to damage the king.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
        <p>
            After this they went to rest; however, they still sent a guard for the bridge. And no-one attacked them from any part, and none of the enemy came to the bridge, as the guards reported.
        </p>
    </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
        <p>
            But at dawn they crossed the bridge, which was made of thirty-seven vessels fastened together; they took all possible precautions, for some Hellenes from Tissaphernes brought word that they meant to attack while they were crossing. But this was false; however, as they were crossing, Glus appeared with some scouts to see if they were crossing the river, and when he saw, he galloped away.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
        <p>
            <milestone unit="para"/> 
            From the Tigris they marched four stages, 20 leagues, to the River Physcos, breadth 100 feet; there was a bridge across. There also was a large city, named Opis. There the Hellenes were met by the bastard brother of Cyros and Artaxerxes, from Susa and Ecbatana, bringing a large army to support the king; and halting his army, he watched the Hellenes passing by. </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
        <p>Clearchos led them two abreast, sometimes marching and sometimes halting. As long as the leading section of the army halted, so long there must be a halt through the whole army; so as the command ran down, the whole army seemed to be enormous, even to the Hellenes themselves, and the Persian was dumbfounded at the sight.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
        <p>
            Thence they marched through Media seven desert stages, 30 leagues, as far as the villages of Parysatis, the mother of Cyros and Artaxerxes. These Tissaphernes, in mockery of Cyros, gave over to the Hellenes to plunder, but no captives to be taken. There was plenty of corn there and sheep and other things.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
        <p>
            From there they marched four desert stages, 20 leagues, keeping the Tigris on the left. At the first stage beyond the river was an inhabited city named Cainai, large and prosperous, from which the natives used to bring over on rafts of skin, loaves, cheeses, and wine.
            <pb n="48"/>
        </p>
    </div>
    </div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p>
            After this they reached the River Zapatas, breadth 400 feet. There they stayed three days; at this time there were suspicions, but no manifest plot.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p>
            So Clearchos resolved to approach Tissaphernes, and see whether he could stop these suspicions before they brought war. He sent word that he wished to meet him.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
        <p>
            Tissaphernes readily invited him to come. When they went, Clearchos said:

            "I know, Tissaphernes, that oaths have been sworn and pledges given between us that we will not harm each other; but I see you watching us like enemies, and we, seeing that, watch you too.         </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
        <p>But as by my inquiry I cannot perceive that you try to do us any hurt, and I know well that we never think even of such a thing, I thought it best to speak to you in hopes we may get rid of our mutual distrust.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
        <p>
            "For I know it has often happened that either from slander or from suspicion men have been frightened of each other, and wishing to get in first before they suffer, they have done incurable mischief to others who were not intending to do anything of the sort, nor indeed wishing to do it.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
        <p>
            "I think such misunderstandings are best ended by meeting face to face; so here I am, to assure you that you have no reason to distrust us.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
        <p>
            "The first and chiefest thing is, that our oaths before heaven stop us from being enemies; I could never deem one happy who knows he has disregarded his oath. In war against heaven, what speed could save? What place could be a refuge? How could one escape? What darkness could he run to? What stronghold could receive him? All things in every place are in God’s hands, God equally rules all.         </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
        <p>That is what I think about the oaths, and about the gods before whom we made our pact of friendship and deposited it there; but of human things, I think at this present you are the best thing we have.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
        <p>
            "For with you every road is easy, every river can be passed, there is no want of provisions. Without you every road goes through darkness, for we know nothing about it; every river is hard to cross, every crowd terrible, and most terrible of all the desert, all full of want.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
        <p>
            "If indeed we were so mad as to kill you, by killing our benefactor should we not bring into the ring against us that most mighty champion in reserve, the king himself?
        </p>
         <p>
            "Now for myself: let me tell you what high hopes and prospects I should rob myself of, if I tried to do you any harm.         </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
        <p>I wished Cyros to be my friend because I thought him most able to benefit anyone he might wish; but you I see now in his place. You hold the power and domain of Cyros and keep your own besides; and the king’s power, which was Cyros’s enemy, is your ally."
        </p>
    </div>
    

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
        <p>
            "This being so, who is so mad that he does not wish to be your friend? Besides, I will tell you reasons why I have some hope that you will wish to be mine."
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
        <p>
            "I know the Mysians are a nuisance to you, and I think I could make them humble with the force I have here. I know about the Pisidians too; and there are many other nations like that, which I think I could make to cease from troubling your happiness. The Egyptians, too, I understand you Persians are very angry with them; and I don’t see any force which could help you to punish them better than this I now have."
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
        <p>
            "Then again, take your own neighbours; if you wished to be a friend you could be the greatest friend, and suppose anyone annoyed you, as master you might turn upon him if you had us to serve you, for we should serve you, not for the pay, but for the gratitude we should owe for saving us."
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
        <p>
            "When I think over all this in my mind it seems astonishing that you distrust us, and I would gladly hear you tell me by name who is an orator clever enough to persuade you that we are plotting against you."
            Clearchos said these words. Tissaphernes then replied:
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
        <p>
            "Indeed I am glad, Clearchos, to hear your sensible words. For if that is your mind, I think you would be your own enemy as well as mine if you should plan mischief against me. Listen, and I will show you that you have just as little reason to distrust either the king or me."
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
        <p>
            "If we wished to destroy you, do you think we lack cavalry or infantry or armament, quite enough to damage you with no fear of suffering any harm in return? 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
        <p>Then do you think there would be no suitable places for attack? Remember all the plains which you traverse with such hardship even while they are friendly. Look at all the mountains you must cross, which we could occupy before you and make impassable. Think of all the great rivers, where we can regulate our portions and decide how many we want to fight with. Some of them you could not possibly cross unless we ferried you over!"
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
        <p>
            "Even if we should fail in all these, at least let me remind you, ‘Fire is stronger than fruit’; we could burn up all the crops and enlist famine against you—however strong you are, you couldn’t fight that!"
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
        <p>
            "Then while we have so many ways to make war upon you, all without danger for ourselves, why should we choose the only way which is impious before heaven, the only way which is disgraceful before men?"
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
        <p>
            "Men must be wholly helpless and resourceless and constrained by necessity, and they must be wicked too, if they are willing to use perjury to God and treachery to men in doing a thing. No, Clearchos, we are not so unreasonable or so foolish as that."
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
        <p>
            "Well, then, if we could destroy you, why did we not go so far? I assure you the reason was my passion to be trusted by the Hellenes. Cyros came up country trusting to this mercenary force, and I wished to go down again, made strong by benefits done to his same force."
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
        <p>
            "How you can be useful to me you have said, at least partly, but the greatest thing of all, I know: the tiara on the head only the king may wear upright, but the tiara on the heart perhaps with you to help another might find it easy to wear so."
        </p>
    </div>
    

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
        <p>
            Clearchos thought he spoke honestly, and he said: “Then since we are such friends, those who try by calumny to make us enemies are worthy of death?”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
        <p>
            “Yes,” Tissaphernes said, “and if your captains and your officers will come here, I will tell you openly who accuse you of plotting against me and my army.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
        <p>
            “Then I will bring them all,” said Clearchos, “and I will reveal to you also where I hear this about you.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
        <p>
            After this conversation Tissaphernes made a great fuss of him, and asked him to stay, and they dined together.
   
            Next day when Clearchos came back to the camp it was clear that he thought himself great in friendship with Tissaphernes. He reported what he had said. “We must all go,” he said, “as he asks, and any of us who are proved to be calumniating him, must be punished as traitors and enemies to us all.”      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
        <p>But he suspected the calumniator was Menon; for he knew that he and Ariaios had meetings with Tissaphernes, and that he was intriguing and scheming against himself in order to get command of the whole army and make himself a friend to Tissaphernes.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
        <p>
            Clearchos also wished that the whole army should follow his will, and that troublesome persons should be out of the way. But some of the soldiers protested that the captains and officers ought not all to go and trust Tissaphernes.      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
        <p>But Clearchos insisted strongly, until he arranged that five captains should go and twenty other officers; and about two hundred soldiers went with them to do their marketing.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31">
        <p>
            When they reached the door of Tissaphernes the captains were invited in, Proxenos the Boeotian, Menon the Thessalian, Agias the Arcadian, Clearchos the Laconian, Socrates the Achaean; the other officers stayed at the door.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32">
        <p>
            A little while afterwards, at one signal, those inside were seized, and those outside were cut down. Soon after a number of barbarian horsemen rode about the plain, and killed every Hellene they met, slave or free.      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33">
        <p>The men wondered at this display of horsemanship from the camp, and did not know what to make of it until a fugitive came in, Nicarchos, an Arcadian, wounded in the belly and holding his bowels in his hands, and told what had happened.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34">
        <p>
            Then all the Hellenes ran for their arms, all aghast, expecting they would come to the camp instantly.      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35">
        <p>They did not all come, but Ariaios and Artaozos and Mithradates came, who had been Cyros’s most trusted friends; the interpreter of the Hellenes said he saw and recognized the brother of Tissaphernes with them. They were attended by some three hundred Persians in corselets.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36">
        <p>
            When these came near they called for any captain or officer that they might deliver the king’s message.
        </p>
    </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37">
        <p>
            After this two captains came out, carefully guarded, Cleanor the Orchomenian, and Sophainetos the Stymphalian, and with them Xenophon the Athenian, who wished to hear news of Proxenos; Cheirisophos happened to be absent in a village with others getting provisions.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38">
        <p>
            When they stood within hearing, Ariaios said: “Listen, Hellenes. Clearchos was shown to have perjured himself and broken the truce; therefore he has been punished and he is dead; but Proxenos and Menon, because they reported his plot, are in high honour. You lay down your arms, that is the king’s demand; he says they are his, because they belonged to Cyros his slave.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39">
        <p>
            The Hellenes made Cleanor their spokesman to answer, and he said, “You abominable wretch Ariaios, and you others who were friends of Cyros, have you no shame before gods and men? You swore the oath to have the same friends and enemies as we did, and you have betrayed us, with Tissaphernes, that most impious and godless villain! You have murdered the very man to whom you gave your oath, and you have betrayed us all, and you join our enemies to come against us!”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40">
        <p>
            Ariaios replied, “Because Clearchos was proved to have plotted first against Tissaphernes and Orontas, and against us all who are with them.” Xenophon rejoined upon this, 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41">
        <p>
            “Clearchos, then, is punished, if he broke the truce contrary to his oath, for the perjured are justly put to death, but what of Proxenos and Menon? They are your benefactors, and they are our captains, then send them here; for it is clear that being friends to both parties they will try to advise the best both for you and for us.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42">
        <p>
            The barbarians discussed this for a long time, and then went away without answering a word.
        </p>
    </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p>
            The captains, captured thus, were carried up to the king and there beheaded. One of them, Clearchos, was a true soldier and war was his passion, as all agreed who formed their opinions from personal knowledge.     </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p>As long as the war lasted between Lacedaimon and Athens, he stayed at home; but when peace came he persuaded his own city that the Thracians were injuring the Hellenes; and having managed as well as he could with the ephors, he sailed to make war on the Thracians beyond Chersonese and Perinthos.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
        <p>
            However, the ephors changed their minds as soon as he had set out, and tried to turn him back from the Isthmus; but he would not obey them any longer, and sailed away to the Hellespont.     </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
        <p>Consequently, he was sentenced to death by the Spartan government for disobedience to orders. He was already a banished man when he came to Cyros. What arguments he used to persuade Cyros have been written elsewhere<note>It is not known where</note>; at least Cyros gave him 10,000 darics. 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
        <p>
           He took the money, but he did not turn to a lazy life: no, with this money he collected a force and made war on the Thracians, and conquered them in battle; he ravaged them after that, and went on with the war until Cyros wanted his army—then he went off to make war again under him.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
        <p>
            These seem to me the doings of a man whose passion was war. When he could have kept at peace without shame or damage, he chose war; when he could have been idle, he wished for hard work that he might have war; when he could have kept wealth without danger, he chose to make it less by making war; there was a man who spent upon war as if it were a darling lover or some other pleasure.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
        <p>
            So war was his passion; and he seemed a true soldier, because he loved perils; ready to lead against the enemy by day or by night, and he kept his head in danger, as those with him agreed one and all in every place. 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
        <p>
           He had also the repute of a true leader, as far as was possible for a man of his character. He was able to think out ways to get provisions for his forces, and then to get them; and he was able to fix firmly in their minds that Clearchos must be obeyed.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
        <p>
            This he did by being severe; he was grim to look at and harsh in voice, he punished heavily and sometimes in anger, so that now and again he was sorry for it. 
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
        <p>
           And he punished on principle, for he thought an unpunished army was good for nothing; indeed, he used to say that a soldier ought to fear his commander more than the enemy, if he was to keep guard, or keep his hand off friends, or attack the enemy without excuses.
        </p>
    </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
   <p>In danger, however, the soldiers wished absolutely to obey him and chose no other; 
   at such times his grimness appeared brightness, they said, his severity seemed strength against the enemy, 
   so that they thought it salvation rather than severity.   </p>
    </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
   <p>But when the danger was past,
   <pb n="55"/>
 many left him if there was an opportunity to pass over to other commanders; for he had no charm, and he was always severe and cruel, 
   so the soldiers felt towards him as boys towards a schoolmaster.   </p>
    </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
   <p>Indeed, he never found any to follow him for affection and friendship; 
   but those who were put under his charge by some authority, or through need or some other constraint, he found completely obedient.</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
   <p>But when they began to succeed in conquering an enemy under him, his men had strong motives to make them useful; 
   for one thing, they felt confident of victory, and for another, they feared punishment from him, which made them obedient.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
   <milestone unit="para"/>
   <p>Such was Clearchos as a commander; but it was said he did not like very much to be commanded himself. 
   He was about fifty years old when he died.</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
   <milestone unit="para"/>
   <p>Proxenos the Boeotian ever since the days of his youth had longed to become a man capable of doing great things; 
   and because of this longing he paid his fees to Gorgias of Lentinoi. 
   <note>the rhetorician, who asked 100 minae</note></p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
   <p>After being with Gorgias he thought himself at once quite capable of being a ruler, 
   and since he was a friend of the first men of his day he thought himself the equal of any man as a benefactor. 
   In this spirit he took part in the business of Cyros; he believed he should get a great name from this, and great power and wealth. 
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
   <p>   Yet although he longed so much for these great things, all the same it was quite clear that he did not wish to get any of them by injustice; 
   with justice and honour he thought these things ought to be got, but not without.</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
   <p>To rule gentlemen he was well able, but still he could not put fear or respect for himself into his soldiers. 
   Indeed, he had rather respect for the soldiers than they had for him, and he obviously feared rather to be disliked by the soldiers than the soldiers feared to disobey him.</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
   <p>He thought that to praise one who did well, and not to praise the offender, was enough to make a ruler and the reputation of a ruler. 
   Therefore the gentlemen<pb n="56"/> among his associates liked him and wished him well, but common men schemed against him and thought him easy game. 
   When he died, he was about thirty years old.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
   <p>
      <milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>There was no doubt about Menon the Thessalian<note>This is again Plato’s Menon, who is a happier figure in those pages.</note>; 
      it was obvious that he desired with all his heart to be rich, that he desired to rule in order that he might get more, that he desired to be honoured in order that he might make more profit. 
      He wished to be a friend to the most powerful that he might do wrong and not be punished. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
   <p>He believed that the shortest way to accomplish what he desired was perjury and lying and deceit, 
      but simplicity and truth were just foolishness.
   </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
   <p>
      It was clear that he had affection for no one, but he obviously plotted against any he called friend. 
      <milestone unit="para"/>He never laughed at an enemy, but he always talked as though he was laughing at all his associates.  </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
   <p>
      He had no designs against the possessions of his enemies, for he thought it was difficult to get hold of things well-guarded; 
      but he believed he was the sole discoverer of how easy it is to get hold of the unprotected, that is, what his friends had.
   </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
   <p>
      If he found out that any were perjured and dishonest, he feared them as being well-armed; but pious men, and those who practised truth, 
      he tried to use as being cowards.    </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
   <p>As others pride themselves on godliness and truth and honesty, so Menon prided himself on his power to deceive, 
      to fabricate falsehoods, to mock at his friends. 

      If a man was not unscrupulous, he always thought him one of the uneducated. If he wanted to make himself first in the friendship of any, 
      he thought it should be done by slandering those who were first.    </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
   <p>To make his soldiers obedient, his principle was to share in their misdeeds; 
      he expected to be honoured and courted if he showed that he would and could do most in that line.

      If ever anyone held aloof, he called it a real kindness that he had not destroyed him while they were friends. 
         </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
   <p>
      There are indeed certain obscure charges against him which may not be true, but here are some things which everyone knows.
   </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
   <p>
      <pb n="57"/>He was in the bloom of his youth when he got command of the mercenaries from Aristippos; 
      he became very intimate with Ariaios, who was a barbarian, because the man liked handsome lads; 
      he himself, while yet beardless, had a bearded favourite in Tharypas. 
   </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
   <p>
      When his fellow-generals were put to death for marching with Cyros against the king, he was not put to death although he had done the same; 
      but after the death of the others, he was punished with death by the king, not beheaded like Clearchos and the rest, which is thought to be the quickest death, 
      but it is said that he was kept alive for a year and tortured until he died the death of a malefactor.
   </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
   <p>
      <milestone unit="para"/>Agias the Arcadian and Socrates the Achaian were also put to death. 
      No one had a bad word to say of these, either as soldiers or as friends. Both were about five-and-thirty years of age.
   </p>
</div>
</div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="3">
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>After the captains had been seized, and the officers and men who were their escort had been cut down, 
         the Hellenes were in despair, full of anxiety. There they were at the king’s door, and round them everywhere so many nations and cities of the enemy. 
         No-one now would provide them a market; they were distant from Hellas more than a thousand miles, with no guide for the road. Impassable rivers 
         crossed the homeward way, and they had been deserted even by the natives who had come up-country with Cyros.

         <milestone unit="para"/>They were left alone without one single horseman to help them, so that it was clear that if they were victorious they could kill no-one, 
         and if they were worsted not one of them would be left.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>These thoughts passed through their minds and made them spiritless. Few of them tasted food 
         that evening, few lit a fire; many of them never came into camp that night, but they rested each where he chanced to be. They could not sleep for sorrow, 
         longing for home and parents, for wives and children, which they never expected to see again. In this state they all tried to rest.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>There was in the army an Athenian, Xenophon, who
         <pb n="59"/>came with them neither as captain nor officer nor man, but Proxenos had invited him to come, being an old family friend. 
         Proxenos promised, if he would come, to introduce him to Cyros, who was, he said, more than home and country to himself.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>Xenophon read his letter, 
         and consulted Socrates the philosopher about this trip. Socrates had a suspicion that there might be some state objection to his being friendly with 
         Cyros, because Cyros had favoured the Lacedaimonians in their war against Athens; so he advised Xenophon to go to Delphi and inquire of the oracle 
         about this journey.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>Accordingly Xenophon went and asked Apollo what god he should sacrifice and pray to, that he might best accomplish the journey he had in mind, 
         and come back safe and successful. Apollo named the gods to whom he must sacrifice.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>When he came back he told the oracle to Socrates. But Socrates blamed him because he had not asked first whether it was better for him to go or to stay, 
         but just decided to go, and then asked how he could best do it. “But,” said he, “since you did ask that, you must do what the god bids.”      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
         So Xenophon sacrificed to those gods as he was directed, and set sail; and at Sardis he found Proxenos and Cyros on the point of going up country, 
         and then he was introduced to Cyros.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>Proxenos urged him to stay, and Cyros urged him too, and promised he would send him home as soon as the campaign was over. 
         The expedition was said to be against the Pisidians;      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>and so he joined it, being thus deceived—but not by Proxenos, for he did not know of the attack 
         to be made upon the king, nor did anyone else of the Hellenes except Clearchos.

         <milestone unit="para"/>However, when they got as far as Cilicia, it seemed to be clear to all that they were marching against the king. 
         Most of them followed for shame of one another and Cyros, although they feared the journey and went against their will; and one of these was Xenophon.
         <pb n="60"/>      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>And now in their desperate plight, he was unhappy like the rest and could not sleep; but he did snatch a nap, and then he saw a dream. 
         He thought there was lightning and a thunderbolt fell on his father’s house, and all was in a blaze.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>He woke at once in terror; the dream he judged to be good in one way, because amid troubles and dangers he seemed to see a great light from Zeus, 
         but in another way he feared, because he considered the dream to come from Zeus the king and the blaze of fire seemed to be all round, so he feared 
         difficulties would fence him in all round, and he might not be able to get out of the country of the king.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>But what such a dream really means may be seen from what happened afterwards; and this is what happened. As soon as he was awake, 
         the first thought that came into his head was, “Why do I lie here? The night is going on, and with daylight it is likely the enemy will come. 
         If we fall into the power of the king, now we must see the most cruel sights, and feel the most terrible pains, and die by violence—and how can it be helped? 
             </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
         But how are we to defend ourselves? No-one is preparing for that, no-one cares about that, but we lie here as if it were possible to live in peace and quiet! 
         What about me then? What captain from what country do I expect to do that? Am I waiting till I grow old enough myself—and how old? 
         I shall never be any older at all, if I give myself up to the enemy to-day.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>Then he got up, and first called together the underofficers of Proxenos. When they were collected he said: 
         “Gentlemen, I cannot sleep and I don’t think you can; and I can’t lie here when I see what a plight we are in.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
   <p>
      It is clear that the enemy did not show us open war until they thought they had everything well prepared; 
      and no one among us takes the pains to make the best possible resistance.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
   <p>
      Yet if we give way and fall into the king’s power, what do we expect our fate will be? 
      When his own half-brother was dead, the man cut off his head and cut off his hand and stuck them up on a pole. 
      We have no one to plead for us, and we marched here to make the king a slave or to kill him if we could, 
      and what do you think our fate will be?
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
   <p>
      Would he not go to all extremes of torture to make the whole world afraid of making war on him? 
      Why, we must do anything to keep out of his power!
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
   <p>
      While the truce lasted, I never ceased pitying ourselves, I never ceased congratulating the king and his army. 
      What a vast country I saw, how large, what endless provisions, what crowds of servants, how many cattle and sheep, 
      what gold, what raiment!
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
   <p>
      But when I thought of these our soldiers—we had no share in all these good things unless we bought them, 
      and few had anything left to buy with; and to procure anything without buying was debarred by our oaths. 
      While I reasoned like this, I sometimes feared the truce more than the war now.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
   <p>
      However, now they have broken the truce, there is an end both to their insolence and to our suspicion. 
      There lie all these good things before us, prizes for whichever side proves the better men; 
      the gods are the judges of the contest, and they will be with us, naturally.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
   <p>
      These men are perjured before them, while we saw so many good things and kept strictly away from them 
      because of our oaths sworn to the gods; therefore we may enter the contest, it seems to me, with much better hearts than they can.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
   <p>
      Besides, our bodies are better fitted than theirs for bearing cold and heat and hardship; 
      and our souls are better, thank God! They are men easier to wound and to kill than we are if the gods give us victory as before.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
   <p>
      Perhaps others are now thinking the same, but in heaven’s name don’t let us wait for someone else to come and 
      pat us on the back and say, Go it. Here’s a grand enterprise! Let us take the lead and show the others how to be brave! Show yourselves the best of officers, and as worthy to be captains as the captains themselves! 
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
   <p>
      Count on me, if you are 
      willing to make the start; I will follow you, or if you order me to lead, I will not make my youth an excuse, but I think 
      I am old enough to keep danger from myself!
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
   <p>
      <milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The officers on hearing this address all asked him to be their leader, except a certain Apollonides who spoke in the Boeotian dialect. 
      He said it was all nonsense to pretend that any safety could be found except with the king’s consent, if that could be had, and at the same time 
      he began to speak of the difficulties. But Xenophon cut him short and said:
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
   <p>
      “Man, I’m amazed at you! You have eyes to see, but you understand not; you have ears to hear, but you remember not! 
      You were there with the others, I think, when the king was so proud after the death of Cyros, and sent to demand our arms. 
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
   <p>
        We refused to give them up, but went and encamped beside him. What didn’t he do! Sent ambassadors, asked for a truce, 
      gave provisions till he got it!
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
   <p>
      And when the captains and officers did what you tell us to do, and went for a conference without arms, trusting to this truce—where are they now? 
      Beaten, stabbed, insulted, the poor devils can’t even die, though that is what they long for!
 
      And you know all this, and you say those who urge resistance are talking nonsense, and you tell us to go there again and try persuasion!
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
   <p>
      In my opinion, gentlemen, we should not admit such a man into our ranks. Strip him of his command, take away his equipment, 
      and let him go wherever he pleases. Such a man is a disgrace not only to his city but to all Hellas, for though he is a Hellene, 
      he behaves in such a manner as this!
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31">
   <p>
      Then Agasias the Stymphalian broke in and said: 
      “But this fellow has nothing to do at all with Boeotia or Hellas; 
      I have noticed that both his ears are bored, like a Lydian’s.” 
      
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32">
   <p>And so they were; accordingly, they drove him away.
      The others went the rounds; wherever a captain was in some post they called him along, 
      wherever there was none, the second-in-command, or where a lieutenant was left alive, the lieutenant.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33">
   <p>
      When all were collected, they seated themselves in front of the place of arms; 
      they were about one hundred captains and other officers. It was about midnight now.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34">
   <p>
      Then Hieronymos of Elis, the eldest of Proxenos’s officers, began to speak. He said: 
      “Gentlemen, captains and officers of our army, seeing the state we are in, we thought it best to meet and to invite you, 
      that we might devise some good plan amongst us. I call on you, Xenophon, to speak as you did to us.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35">
   <p>
      Then Xenophon said: “Well, we all know that the king and Tissaphernes have seized all of us they could, 
      and it is clear they are planning to destroy us if they can. My opinion is that we ought to do anything and everything not to fall into the power 
      of these barbarians, but turn the tables on them.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36">
   <p>
      “Let me point out to you, then, that you now here assembled have a grand opportunity. 
      All these soldiers have their eyes on you. If they see you are discouraged, they will all be cowards; 
      but if you show that you are making preparations against the enemy, and if you call on them, you may be sure they will follow you and try to imitate you.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37">
   <p>
      “Perhaps it is fair to expect you to be a bit better than they are. You are captains, you see, or you are in command of troops and companies, 
      and while there was peace, you had more wealth and honor; then now when war has come, we must ask you to be better than the mob, 
      and to plan and labor for their behalf, if necessary.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38">
   <p>
      “Now, first of all, I think you will do the whole army a great service if you take care at once to appoint captains and officers 
      in the place of those who have been lost. For it is true one may say universally that without commanders nothing good or useful could ever be done: 
      good discipline always saves, but disorder has destroyed many.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39">
   <p>
      “When you have appointed as many commanders as are wanted, assemble all the other soldiers and encourage them; 
      that will be just what they want now.    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40">
   <p>Perhaps you have noticed yourselves how crestfallen they were when they came into camp, 
      how crestfallen they went on guard; in such a state, I don’t know what you could do with them, either by night or by day.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41">
   <p>
      “But if someone could turn their minds from wondering what will happen to them, and make them wonder what they could do, 
      they will be much more cheerful.    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42">
   <p>You know, I am sure, that not numbers or strength brings victory in war; 
      but whichever army goes into battle stronger in soul, their enemies generally cannot withstand them.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43">
   <p>
      “I have noticed also myself, gentlemen, that when men seek for nothing in warfare but only life at all costs, 
      they are generally the ones to die, and that with disgrace and ignominy; but when they recognize that all men must die, for this is their common lot, 
      and strive only to die with honor, these I generally see growing to old age, and while they live, much happier.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44">
   <p>
      “Learn this lesson yourselves, for now is the time we need it: be men yourselves, and encourage others to do the same.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45">
   <p>
      With these words, he sat down; and after him, Cheirisophos rose and said: 
      “All I knew of you before, my dear Xenophon, was just that I heard you were an Athenian; but now I admire you for what you say and what you do, 
      and I wish there were many more like you—that would be a public benefit.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46">
   <p>
      “And now, gentlemen,” he went on, “don’t let us waste time; dismiss and choose commanders, those who need them, 
      then come back here to the middle of our camp, and bring the selected men. After that, we will summon all the troops to a meeting there. 
      And we must have Tolmides the herald there too.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47">
   <p>
      As he said this, he got up and went to do what was necessary without delay. Then officers were chosen: in place of Clearchos, 
      Timasion the Dardanian; in place of Socrates, Xanthicles the Achaian; in place of Agias, Cleanor the Arcadian; 
      in place of Menon, Philesios the Achaian; in place of Proxenos, Xenophon the Athenian.
   </p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When these had been elected, it was almost dawn, and the commanders came forward. They decided to set the watch and to convene the men. 
         When the soldiers were all there, first Cheirisophos the Lacedaimonian got up and spoke as follows:
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>
         “Soldiers, this is a dangerous time, when we have lost such captains and officers and men; and besides, our former allies, Ariaios and his men, have betrayed us. 
         But we must face the dangers, and prove good men, and not give in, but try to save ourselves by a handsome victory if we can. 
     </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
              If not, at least let us die with honour, but let us never fall into our enemies’ hands alive; for I think we should suffer such things as the gods would do to their enemies.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
         After him Cleanor the Orchomenian rose and said: “You see, men, the king’s perjury and impiety! You see the treachery of Tissaphernes! 
         He said he was near neighbour to Hellas, and would do so much to save us, he swore solemn oaths to us himself, he gave us pledges himself, 
         and then he deceived us himself—seized our captains, feared not the God of Guests, but invited Clearchos to sit at his table, 
         and then made this very act the means of destroying those men!
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         Ariaios again—we would have made him king, we gave and received pledges to be true to each other, but he did not fear God. 
         Cyros alive honoured him highly, but he had no respect for Cyros dead; now he has deserted to the bitterest enemies of Cyros, and tries to ruin the friends of Cyros! 
              </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
         These men may the gods punish; but we, seeing this, must not be deceived by these men again. 
         We must fight our strongest, and leave our fate in the hands of the gods.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Then Xenophon rose; he was arrayed for war in his finest dress. “If the gods grant victory,” he thought, 
         “the finest adornments are most proper for such a victory; if I must die, after grand ambitions I would meet my end in grandeur.” 
         Then he began as follows:
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
         “The perjury and treachery of the barbarians Cleanor has spoken of, and I think you know it yourselves. 
         Then if we wish to be friends with them again, we must feel very much disheartened when we see what our captains have suffered when they trusted themselves to them in good faith. 
         But if we have in mind to punish them in arms for what they have done, and to be henceforth in war with them out and out, 
         then with God’s help there are many good hopes of safety.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         While he was speaking someone sneezed<note>a good omen</note>; the soldiers hearing this, kissed their hands to heaven, and Xenophon said:
         “While we were speaking of safety came an omen of Zeus the Saviour! Then I think we should vow to this god a thanksgiving for salvation as soon as we reach the first friendly country, 
         and vow a sacrifice to the other gods according to our ability. Whoever agrees with this, let him hold up his hand.”
         All held up their hands. Then they made their vow and chanted the battle-hymn. After this matter of piety was settled he began again:
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
         “I am just saying that we have many good hopes of safety. Firstly, we abide by our solemn oaths; 
         but the enemy have perjured themselves and broken the truce contrary to their oaths. It is reasonable, then, that the gods should be against our enemies 
         and should be our own allies; and they are able quickly to make the great small, and easily to save the small in time of danger, if it be their pleasure.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>
         “Next I will remind you of the dangers which our ancestors faced, and you will see that it is proper for you to be good men, 
         and that good men are saved with the gods’ help even from great danger.”

         “The Persians came, you know, with their enormous fleet, to wipe out Athens; but the Athenians dared to stand up to them and conquered them. 
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>
               They had vowed to Artemis to sacrifice as many goats as they should kill Persians; but they could not find enough, so they resolved to sacrifice every year five hundred, 
         and they do so still.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
         “Again later, when Xerxes collected that innumerable host against Hellas, then again our ancestors conquered the ancestors of these men by land and sea. 
         We can see proofs of this in the trophies, but the greatest proof is the freedom of those cities in which you were born and brought up; 
         for you revere no man as master, but only the gods.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
         “Such were your ancestors. I will not say indeed that you are not worthy of them. No, not many days ago you faced these their descendants, 
         many times your number, and conquered them.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>
Then you did your part well, in order to make Cyros king; now that your own life and safety is at stake, 
         I take it you ought to be much better and much more resolute.”
      </p>
   </div>

   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
    <p>
        Moreover, you must be more confident against your enemy. At that time you had no experience of them, yet you dared to attack them with the spirit of your fathers. 
        Now you have found by experience that they will not stand up to you even if they are many times your number. Then why should you fear them?
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
    <p>
        And pray consider it no great loss that Cyros’s men who stood by us once have left us. For they are greater cowards than those whom you beat; 
        at least they took refuge with them when they left us. If people want to be in the front ranks of a flight, I prefer to see them in our enemies’ ranks rather than in ours.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
    <p>
        If any of you is downhearted because we have no cavalry but the enemy have many, remember that their ten thousand cavalry are only ten thousand men. 
        No-one ever died in battle from the kick or the bite of a horse; the men make them do whatever they do in battle.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
    <p>
        In fact, we have a safer carrier than cavalry; there they hang on their horses fearing a fall as well as a foe, but we stand on the ground, 
        and we can hit harder if anyone attacks, and aim better. The cavalry have indeed one advantage; they can cut and run more safely!
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
    <p>
        Perhaps you feel bold enough about battle, but you are anxious because Tissaphernes will not guide us any longer and the king will not provide a market. 
        Think a moment whether it is better to have Tissaphernes for a guide, when he is clearly planning mischief against us, or any men we can catch to make them guide us; 
        they know that if they do us wrong, their lives and bodies are at stake.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
    <p>
        And provisions: is it better to buy from the market which those men provided, small measure for big price, when we have not even the price now; 
        or to take it ourselves if we beat them, with any measure we like?
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
    <p>
        Perhaps you recognize we are better off as it is, but think the rivers an impassable obstacle; you consider you have been badly deceived when you crossed them. 
        But think whether this is not really the most foolish thing which the barbarians have done. All rivers are passable when you come near the source, hardly knee-deep, 
        although they may be impassable far down.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
    <p>
        But assume that the rivers will not let us across and no guide can be found, even so we must not lose heart. Look at the Mysians; 
        we should not say they are better than we are, but we know there are many large and prosperous cities full of them, in the king’s country, without his leave. 
        We know the same of Pisidians, and we have seen ourselves that Lycaonians have seized the strong places in the plains and reap his country.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
    <p>
        So with us: I think we ought not to show that we have set out for home, but make preparations to live here. 
        I know quite well that the king would give plenty of guides to the Mysians, and hostages for honest dealing, and he would make roads for them 
        even if they wished to depart in four-horse chariots. Be sure he would think himself thrice blessed to do it for us, if he saw us preparing to settle down! 
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
    <p>
        But I am afraid that if we once learn to live idle in luxury, 
        and to dally with the fine big women and girls of the Medes and Persians, we may be like the lotus-eaters and forget the way home!
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
    <p>
        I think, then, that we must first try to reach Hellas and our own people, and show the Hellenes that they are poor only because they want to be, 
        when they could bring their paupers over here and see them rich. But don’t forget, men, that all these good things belong to the conquerors;
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
    <p> 
        and now it is necessary to say how we can travel most safely and fight most successfully.
        First of all, then, I propose that we burn the wagons we have, that the baggage-train may not be our captain, and we may go where is best for the army. 
        Next, burn the tents too: for these are a nuisance to carry, they don’t help us to fight or to find provisions.     </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
    <p>
Further, let us get rid of superfluous baggage, 
        keeping only what we need for battle or eating or drinking; so the greatest number of us will be under arms, and as few as possible carrying baggage. 
        You know, of course, that if we are beaten, someone else owns all our goods; if we win, we may call the enemy our porters.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
    <p>
        It remains to say what I think is the chief thing of all. You see that the enemy dared not make war upon us until they had seized our leaders. 
        They believed that while the commanders were there, and while we obeyed, we were able to defeat them; when they took our commanders, 
        they thought we should be destroyed by anarchy and disorder.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
    <p>
        Very well: the commanders must be much more careful than before, and the commanded must be more obedient than before.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31">
    <p>
        and if anyone disobeys, we must vote that each and all of you must help the commander to punish. So the enemy will find themselves mightily mistaken: 
        for this day they will see ten thousand Clearchoses instead of one, who will never permit anyone to be a coward.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32">
    <p>
        “But now it is high time for me to finish; perhaps the enemy will be here soon. Then let those who think I am right support me at once, that my proposals may be carried out. 
        Or if anyone has anything better, let him speak up boldly and say so, even if he is a private soldier, for our common safety is our common need.”
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33">
    <p>
        After this Cheirisophos said, “If we need anything else, beside what Xenophon says, we can do it by and by; but I think it best to carry these proposals at once. 
        Whoever agrees, let him hold up a hand.” 
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34">
    <p>All held up their hands.
        Then Xenophon rose again and said, “Men, listen to something else I have to propose. It is clear that we must march where we can find provisions, 
        and I hear there are good villages not more than ten miles away.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35">
    <p>
        Then we should not be surprised if the enemy follow us when we go, as cowardly dogs chase and bite those who pass, if they can, 
        but run away if they pursue.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36">
    <p>
        Then it is safe perhaps to march in a hollow square, with the armed men outside and the baggage and crowd of camp followers safer in the middle. 
        Suppose we decide who is to lead the square, and keep order in front, and who is to be on the flanks, and who to bring up the rear, 
        we shall not have to consider when the enemy come, but we can just use the arrangements.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37">
    <p>
        If anyone sees anything better, let us do as he says: otherwise let Cheirisophos lead the van, since he is a Lacedaimonian, 
        and the two eldest captains see to the flanks; while the youngest, I and Timasion, will take the rear for the present.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38">
    <p>
        We will just try this arrangement, and for the future we can do as may seem best. If anyone has a better plan, let him speak.” 
        As no-one spoke, he said, “Those in favour, hold up a hand.” All agreed.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39">
    <p>
        “Now then,” he said, “dismiss and do it as agreed. And if any of you wants to see his dear ones again, let him remember to be a true man, 
        for that’s the only way to do it. Whoever wants to live, let him try to conquer, for the conquerors kill and the conquered die. 
        If anyone wants riches, let him try to win; for conquerors preserve their own and take the goods of the conquered.”
    </p>
</div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p>
            After these harangues, they went and burnt the wagons and tents; superfluous things they gave to any who wanted
            them, and threw the rest into the fire. This done, they took breakfast.
            <milestone unit="para"/>
            While they were at breakfast, up came Mithradates with about thirty horsemen, and, calling the captains within
            hearing, he spoke as follows:
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p>
            “I was faithful to Cyros, as you know, Hellenes, and now I am friendly to you; indeed I spend my days here in great
            fear. So if I saw that you had some profitable plan for safety, <milestone unit="para"/>
            I would join you with all my servants. Tell me, then, what you have in mind, and regard me as a friend and well-wisher,
            willing to make my journey along with you.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
        <p>
            The captains consulted, and decided to answer this, with Cheirisophos as spokesman: “We are resolved to pass
            through the country doing as little damage as possible, if we are left alone; but if anyone tries to hinder our passage,
            we will fight him as stoutly as we can.”
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
        <p>
            After this Mithradates tried to show them that it was impossible to save their lives except with the king’s consent. Then it became clear
            that he was a spy; for one of the relations of Tissaphernes was there to keep him loyal.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
        <p>
            After this the captains thought it best to proclaim war without parley for as long as they
            were in the enemy country; for they used to come and try to corrupt the soldiers, and they did corrupt one officer,
            Nicarchos the Arcadian, who deserted at night with about twenty men.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
        <p>
            After this, they breakfasted and crossed the Zapatas River;
            <pb n="72"/>
            then began their march in order, with baggage and mob in
            the middle. They had not gone very far when Mithradates
            appeared again with some two hundred horsemen and
            bowmen and slingers, four hundred or so, very light and
            trim.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
        <p>
            He came towards them in friendly fashion, but when
            they were near suddenly there were arrows from both
            horse and foot, and the slingers too wounded many. The
            Hellenic rearguard suffered severely but could do nothing
            in return: for the range of the Cretan bowmen was less than
            the Persian, and besides being bare they had to be inside
            the defenses, and the slingers were beyond the range of their
            javelins.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
        <p>
            So Xenophon ordered pursuit, and the men-at-arms and
            targeteers of his rearguard did pursue, but they caught none
            of the enemy.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
        <p>
            For the Hellenes had no horsemen, and the
            footmen could not catch the enemy footmen with a long
            start in a short run; of course they could not go far from
the army,
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
        <p>
          and the barbarian horsemen shot arrows behind
them as they rode and hit them, besides they had to come
back all that way fighting.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
        <p>
            The result was that they made
no more than three miles or so in all that day, but towards
evening they reached the villages.

<milestone unit="para"/>
Then again there was great discouragement. Cheirisophos
and the older captains blamed Xenophon because he left
the lines to pursue, and risked himself but could do no
harm to the enemy.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
        <p>
Xenophon listened, and said they were
quite right in blaming him, as the result had showed. “But
I was compelled to pursue,” he said, “when I saw that we
suffered so badly by standing still and we could do nothing
in return.
        </p>
    </div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
    <p>
        When we did pursue, what you say is the truth,” says he; “we could do them no damage, and got back with great difficulty.     </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
    <p>
Thank God they had only a small force, so they could not hurt us seriously, but they showed us what we want. 
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
    <p>
Their arrows and slings have such a range
        that the Cretans cannot reach them, nor those who throw by hand; and when we pursue, it is impossible to go far from our army, and in a short space not even a fast runner could catch a runner with a bowshot start.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
    <p>
        Well, then, if we are to keep them from damaging us on the march, we must find slingers and horsemen at once. I hear there are Rhodians in the army, and most of them know how to sling, as they say, and their shot has twice the range of the Persians.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
    <p>
        The Persians use a stone as big as your fist, and so they cannot throw far, but the Rhodians know how to use leaden bullets.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
    <p>
        If we can discover, then, which of them possess a sling and pay them extra for this, and pay for plaiting more slings, and invent some other privilege for those willing to be posted as slingers, perhaps we shall find some useful men.
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
    <p>
        I see also that there are horses with us; I have some myself, some were left by Clearchos, many others which we captured are carrying baggage. If we take the pick of these, and put other animals to carry, we can use the horses for cavalry, and perhaps these will do damage in the pursuit.”
    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
    <p>
        This was agreed to; and that night about 200 slingers were found up, and the next day some 50 horses and horsemen were passed as fitting, and buff jackets and corselets were provided for them, and Lycios the Athenian, Polystratos’ son, was put in command of the horse.
    </p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         They stayed there that day, and on the next began the march earlier than usual, for they had to pass through a ravine where they feared the enemy might attack them in the pass.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>
         When they had passed, Mithradates appeared again with 1,000 cavalry and some 4,000 bowmen and slingers. He had demanded so many from Tissaphernes, and promised that if he got them he would deliver the Hellenes into his hand: he despised them because in the former attack with a small force he had done much damage, as he thought, and suffered nothing at all.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
         When the Hellenes had gone about a mile from the pass, Mithradates came through with his force. Orders had been given which of the targeteers and men-at-arms were to pursue, and the horsemen were told to pursue boldly and a sufficient force would follow.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
         So when Mithradates caught them up, and arrows and slingstones began to come, a trumpet sounded for the Hellenes, and the appointed parties doubled out at once and the horsemen galloped; the enemy did not wait for them but ran back into the ravine.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         In this pursuit, many of the barbarians were killed, and some of the cavalry were taken alive, about eighteen. The dead bodies were mutilated by the Hellenes unbidden, to strike terror into the enemy.
         <note>They only imitated the Persian custom.</note>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
         But the enemy retired after this, and the Hellenes marched unmolested the rest of the day as far as the River Tigris.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         A large deserted city was there, named Larisa, <note>modern Nimrud</note> which had once been inhabited by Medes. The wall of this place was five-and-twenty feet thick, and one hundred high, the whole being two leagues round. It was built of clay bricks, on a stone base twenty feet high.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
         When the Persians took the empire from the Medes the Persian king besieged this place and could not take it in any way; then a cloud covered the sun and hid it until the people escaped, and so it was taken.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         Near this city was a stone pyramid, one hundred feet wide and two hundred high. On this pyramid were many of the natives who had escaped from the villages near.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
         From this place they marched one stage, 6 leagues, to a large deserted fortress named Mespila, <note>Calah, or Nineveh. The first Cyros took it in 558 B.C.</note> formerly inhabited by Medes.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p> The foundation was made of polished stone full of shells, fifty feet wide and fifty high.<note>The circuit was 6 leagues.</note>
         There the king’s wife Medeia, <note>wife of Astyages, the last King of Media</note> is said to have taken refuge when the Medes lost their empire to the Persians.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>
The Persian king besieged this place, but could not take it either by time or by force; but Zeus affrighted the inhabitants by thunder, and so it was taken.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
         From this place they marched one stage, 4 leagues. On this stage Tissaphernes appeared, with his own cavalry and the forces of Orontas, who married the king’s daughter, and the nationals whom Cyros had brought up country with him, and those whom the king’s brothers had brought to support the king; it so appeared to be an immense army.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
         When he was near he stationed some ranks in the rear, and led others along the flanks, but he dared not attack and he wished to run no risk, only gave orders to shoot with bow and sling.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>
         But the Rhodians posted here and there slung their bullets and the bowmen shot their arrows, and not one missed a man (he would have found it hard to miss if he had tried); so Tissaphernes quickly retreated out of range, and the other ranks retreated too.
      </p>
   </div>


   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
   <p>
      For the rest of the day they went on marching, and the barbarians did no harm by their sharpshooting; for the Rhodians had longer range than the Persians, even the bowmen.    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
   <p>
The Persian bows are very large; so the arrows they picked up were useful to the Cretans, who practised with them, shooting high and as far as possible. Plenty of gut was found in the villages, and lead, which they used for the slings.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
   <p>
      So on this day, after the Hellenes had encamped in villages which they found, the barbarians had the worst of that skirmish, and retreated. The day following the Hellenes spent in the villages collecting provisions, for there was plenty of corn there. Next day they marched on over the plain, and Tissaphernes followed, skirmishing.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
   <p>
      Now the Hellenes discovered that the square was a bad formation with the enemy following. If the wings of the square draw together when the road is narrow, or where the hills make it necessary, or a bridge, the armed men must be greatly distressed and march badly; they are squeezed up and disordered at the same time, so they are not easy to manage because they lose discipline.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
   <p>
      Again, when the wings open again after their late distress, the ranks must be separated again, and there are empty spaces between, and all are discouraged with an enemy behind. Or if they have to cross a bridge or some other crossing, each man tries to get over first, and then it is easy for the enemy to attack.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
   <p>
      When the commanders perceived this they made six companies of a hundred men each, and appointed a lieutenant to command each, and officers for each half-company and quarter-company. <note>These were taken from the front or rear rank of the square, which had to be shortened.</note> When the wings drew in on the march these companies fell to the rear so as not to confuse the wings, and they lined up outside the wings.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
   <p>
      When the wings expanded again they filled up the gap in the line between, in line of companies in column if narrow, half-companies if wider, quarter-companies very wide, and so the gap was always filled.    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
   <p>
Thus they were not disordered if they had to cross a ford or a bridge, but the companies crossed in turn; and when they needed the line these were ready. In this way they marched four stages.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
   <p>
       While they were in the fifth they saw a palace and many villages round it, but the road to this led amongst high foothills rolling down from the mountains under which the village lay. The Hellenes were glad indeed to see these mounds, which was natural when the enemy were cavalry.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
   <p>
      By and by they left the plain and went up and down the first mound; then as they were about to go up the second there were the barbarians volleying down the slope from the top javelins, slingstones, and arrows, and the masters could be seen flogging on the men!   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
   <p>
 They wounded many, and defeated the Hellenic light-armed men, and shut them up in the square, so that slingers and bowmen were both quite useless among the mob all that day.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
   <p>
      So the Hellenes had a hard time of it; but when they tried to pursue they could scarcely get to the top in their heavy arms, but the enemy quickly leaped away.    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
   <p>
When they retired to the main army the same things happened; and on the second mound the same again, so that they decided not to move the soldiers from the third mound until they had sent a party of light infantry from the right wing up the mountains.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
   <p>
      As soon as these were posted above the pursuing enemy, the enemy no longer attacked the descending troops for fear they should be cut off and find enemies on both sides.    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
   <p>
So they proceeded for the rest of the day, the army on the road moving over the foot-hills, the others going parallel on the mountain-side, until they reached the villages. They put eight surgeons in charge, for the wounded were many.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31">
   <p>
      They stayed there three days, partly for the sake of the wounded, partly because there was plenty of food, wheatmeal, wine, and barley collected for horses in great quantity. These had been stored up for the regent of the country.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32">
   <p>
      On the fourth day they came down into the plain. When they came upon Tissaphernes with his forces, experience taught them to encamp at the first village they saw and not to march fighting all the while; for there were large numbers unable to fight, the wounded men and their bearers, and those who carried the arms of the bearers.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33">
   <p>
      After they had encamped, when the barbarians began to attack them by their long shots, the Hellenes had much the best of it; for there was a great difference between defending a fixed position and making a running fight on the march.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34">
   <p>
      When late afternoon came it was time for the enemy to depart; for they never encamped at a less distance than seven or eight miles, for fear that they might be attacked in the night. 
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35">
   <p>The Persian army is good for nothing at night.
      Their horses are tied up, and generally hobbled as well, that they may not run away if cast loose; and if there is any disturbance, the Persian has to saddle and bridle his horse, and put on his corselet, and then mount—all difficult things at night when there is a disturbance too. That is why they used to encamp far away from the Hellenes.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36">
   <p>
      When our men noticed that they were about to go and the word went round, the trumpet sounded to pack up. The enemy heard it, and for some time they did not set out, but when it was late go they did, since they thought it did not pay to travel at night and come into camp.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37">
   <p>
      As soon as the Hellenes saw they were really off, they also broke up camp and marched, and did as much as seven miles. So the distance between the two armies was so great, that next day the enemy did not appear at all, nor the day after; but on the fourth day the barbarians had gone ahead by a night march and they seized a high position above the road by which the Hellenes had to go, a mountain spur on the right, under which was the descent into the plain.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38">
   <p>
      When Cheirisophos noticed that the hill had been seized he called Xenophon from the rear, and ordered him to come up in front with the targeteers.    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39">
   <p>
But Xenophon did not bring them, for he saw Tissaphernes appear with his whole army.
      He rode up by himself and asked, “What is it?” The other said, “You can see; the hill above the descent has been seized, and we cannot pass unless we dislodge them.    </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40">
   <p>
Why didn’t you bring the targeteers?” He replied that he did not think it safe to leave the rear undefended when the enemy were in sight there. “Well, at least,” said Cheirisophos, “it’s high time to consider how we can drive the fellows from that hill.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41">
   <p>
      Then Xenophon looked up at the head of the hill above their army, and saw an approach from this to the peak where the enemy were, and he said, “The best thing for us, Cheirisophos, is to go for that height at once. If we seize it the men over the road can’t hold their position. You stay with the army, if you wish, and I shall be glad to try that; or you go, and I'll stay.”   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42">
   <p>
 “Take your choice,” said Cheirisophos, “you have my leave.” Xenophon chose to go. “I’m the younger,” he said, but he asked for a detachment from the van, because it was a long way to bring men from the rear.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43">
   <p>
      So Cheirisophos let him have the light infantry from the van, and took instead those from the centre. He gave him also the 300 picked men that he had himself in the van. They set off at full speed.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44">
   <p>
      As soon as the enemy on the hill perceived their march upon the height, they began to race for this same place.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45">
   <p>
      Then there was a rare din, the Hellenic army cheering on their men, and the army of Tissaphernes cheering theirs.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46">
   <p>
      Xenophon rode by on his horse, shouting, “Men, remember this is a race to Hellas! To your wives and children! One little effort now, and we shall do the rest of our journey without a blow!”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47">
   <p>
      Soteridas the Sicyonian shouted, “It isn’t fair, Xenophon! You ride on a horse, I’m tired out carrying this shield!”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48">
   <p>
      Xenophon, hearing this, jumped off the horse, and pushed the man out of his place, and took the shield from him and went as fast as he could. He had his corselet on, too, as it happened, so it was misery for him. “Look sharp!” he called to the front, “Hurry up!” to the rear, and he could hardly keep up himself.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49">
   <p>
      The other men whacked Soteridas, and pelted him, and gave him plenty of hard words, till they made him take back his shield and march too. Xenophon mounted and rode on again, and led them as long as the path allowed, but when it became too rough he left the horse and made all haste on foot. So they got to the place first, before the enemy.
   </p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         Then the barbarians turned and fled where they could, and the Hellenes occupied the height. The army of Tissaphernes and Ariaios turned away and went by another road. Cheirisophos came down and encamped in a village full of good things. There were many other villages full of good things along the River Tigris.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>
         In the late afternoon suddenly the enemy appeared on the plain, and they cut down some Hellenes who were scattered about the plain plundering; indeed, many herds of animals had been caught while trying to cross the river.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
         There Tissaphernes’ men began to burn the villages, and many of the Hellenes were downhearted for fear they might find no places to get provisions if the burning went on.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
         Cheirisophos had been to the rescue, and he was returning when Xenophon came riding down past the lines and called out as he met them:
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         “There, men of Hellas! Do you see they admit that the country is ours already? They have done what they made us promise not to do in their treaty! We were not to burn the king’s country, and now they are burning it like a foreign country! Well, if they have provisions for themselves, they will see us going there too.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
         “Come, Cheirisophos,” says he, “I think we ought to keep them from burning our country.” Cheirisophos answered, “No, I don’t; let’s burn, too,” says he, “and so they will stop sooner.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         When they reached the camp most were busy about the provisions, but the captains and officers met. All was despondency now. On one side were high mountains, on one side a river so deep that even the spears could not sound it.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
         In this unhappy state a Rhodian man came up and said, “I am ready, sirs, to take you across four thousand men at a time, if you provide me with what I want and pay me one talent.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         “What do you want?” they asked. “Skins I want,” says he, “two thousand skins. I see plenty of sheep and goats and cattle and asses. Flay them and blow up the skins and they will easily give us a crossing.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
         “I will ask you too for the straps you put round the baggage animals. I fasten the skins together with these, I moor each one by tying stones to it and letting them down into the water like anchors, I carry them across by the current in a line and make fast the two ends, I throw wood on the top and earth over that.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>
         “They will not sink, you will see that in a minute: every skin will hold up two men. They won’t slip; the wood and earth will save them.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>
         The captains thought this a pretty notion, but impossible to carry out, for there were numbers of cavalry on the other side to stop them; they would be down on the first lot and would not let them do anything at all.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
         Then the next day they retreated again to the unburnt villages, after burning those they left; so the enemy did not ride after them, but watched them, and seemed to be wondering where they would turn now and what they meant to do.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
         Then most were busy about the provisions, but the captains met again, and collecting their captives questioned them about the country round about, what each district was.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>
         They said that the southern parts lay on the road towards Babylon and Media, by which indeed they had come; towards the east it led to Susa and Ecbatana, where the king is said to spend the summer; across the river to the west it led to Lydia, to Ionia; the road through the mountains and to the north led to the Kurds.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
      <p>
         These they said lived in the mountains and they were warlike; they did not obey the king; that once a royal army had invaded them, 112,000 strong, and not a man came back because of the difficulties of the country. But when there was truce between them and the governor in the plain, “we mix with them,” says he, “and they mix with us.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
      <p>
         After hearing this, the captains seated together those who claimed to know about each part, without revealing which way they meant to go. At last they decided that they were obliged to cross the mountains and get into the country of the Kurds. For the men said that when they had passed through this they would reach Armenia, a large and rich country which was the province of Orontas. Thence they said it would be easy to go wherever they wished.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
      <p>
         Upon this they offered sacrifice, so as to set out whenever it should seem to be the right time; for they feared that the pass over the mountains might have been occupied already. So they sent round the word that after dinner all should pack up and rest, and follow when the command was given.
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
</div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="4">
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         It was about the last watch, and enough of the night was left for them to pass over the plain in darkness; then the word was sent round, and they rose up and marched, and by daylight they had reached the mountains.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
Cheirisophos was leading the army, with all the light-armed troops round him, and Xenophon with men-at-arms of the rearguard followed without any light troops; for there seemed no danger that anyone would follow on the rear of an army going up.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         Cheirisophos reached the summit without seeing any of the enemy; then he led on, and each wave of the army as it rolled up followed into the villages which lie in the dells and corners of the hills.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
By this time all the Kurds had left their houses, with wives and children, and fled into the mountains; but plenty of provisions were to be had, and the houses were provided with huge numbers of brass pots.
         But the Hellenes took none of them, nor did they pursue the people. They spared them in the hope that the Kurds might let them pass through the country as friends, since they were enemies to the king;       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
only they took all the provisions they found, for they had to do it. But the Kurds would not listen to any call, or do any other friendly act.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
         When the last of the Hellenes had come down from the summit into the villages, it was already dark; so narrow was the road that the ascent and descent had taken the whole day. Then some of the Kurds gathered and attacked the last lot, and killed some and wounded others with stones and arrows. They were only a few, for the Hellenic invasion had come as a surprise.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>
But if there had been more, there was danger that a large part of the army would have been lost.

         That night they spent in the open among the villages; but the Kurds lit numbers of fires on the mountains all round in sight of each other.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>
         At dawn the captains and officers of the Hellenes met and decided to take with them only the strongest of their baggage-animals, and no more than were necessary; to leave all the rest, and to let go all captives lately taken that were in the army.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
 Many animals and captives made the pace slow, and many of those in charge of them were out of the fight, and with all these men twice as much provision had to be found and carried. Heralds were sent round to cry these orders.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
         When breakfast was over they marched on; but the captains posted men beside the road at a narrow place: if they found any of the aforesaid things not left behind they took possession. The men mostly obeyed, but some did smuggle away a good-looking boy or woman.
         They marched so far that day, sometimes fighting and sometimes resting; 

               </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>
but next day came a heavy storm, yet they must go on for want of provisions. Cheirisophos led the way, Xenophon guarded the rear. 
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
      <p>
      The enemy attacked them vigorously, and in those narrow places they came close and shot arrows and slingstones, so the Hellenes were compelled to go slow what with chasing and coming back.
          Often Xenophon sent word for a halt, when the enemy attacked vigorously;
      </p>
   </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
      <p>
         Sometimes Cheirisophos halted when the word came, but the last time he would not halt—he went on quickly and sent word to follow, so that it was clear something was up, but there was no time to go and see why he was in a hurry. So it became very much like a flight for the rearguard.
               </p>
   </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
      <p>
 There died a good man, Leonymos, a Laconian, shot with an arrow through shield and corselet into the ribs, and Basias, an Arcadian, right through the head.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
      <p>
         As soon as they reached a halting-place, Xenophon went as he was straight to Cheirisophos, and reproached him: “Why didn’t you halt? We were forced to fly and fight at the same time. And now two fine fellows are dead, and we could not take them up and bury them!” 
               </p>
   </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
      <p>
Cheirisophos answered, “Look at the mountains!” says he. “See! no way up anywhere: this one way you see steep too, and you can see all that mob. They have occupied the pass and they won’t let us get out! 
      </p>
   </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
      <p>
That’s why I made such a hurry and would not halt. I hoped to get there first and seize the pass, and the guides we have say there is no other way.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
      <p>
         Xenophon said, “Well, I have two captives. Those men were so troublesome that I laid ambush, which gave us a minute to breathe also; we killed a good few and took care to take some alive just in order to be guides, because they know the country.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
      <p>
         Then he brought up the men, and questioned them separately, whether they knew any other road than the one they could see. One said no, although many terrors were applied; and since he had nothing useful to say, he was killed in sight of the other.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
      <p>
The second said that the first said he knew no way because a daughter of his was married to a man over there; but he would take them by a road where even animals could go.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
      <p>
         Asked if there were any place ahead difficult to pass, he said there was a height which must be occupied first or nothing could get by.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
      <p>
         Then it was decided to call the officers both of heavy and light infantry, to tell them all this and to ask if anyone were man enough to volunteer. 
               </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
      <p>
From the heavy-armed two Arcadians came forward, Aristonymos, a Methydrian, and Agasias, a Stymphalian, while a third in rivalry, Callimachos, a Parrhasian, offered to lead volunteers from the whole army; “for I know,” says he, “many young men will follow if I lead.” 
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
      <p>
         Then they asked if any of the light-armed officers would join? Aristeas, a Chian, came forward, one who was often useful to the army for enterprises of this kind.
      </p>
   </div>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         It was now late afternoon, and they ordered them to take a bite and go. They tied up the guide and handed him over to these; they arranged that if they could occupy the height, they were to guard it that night and sound the trumpet at dawn. Then the party on the height were to attack the enemy who held the pass, and they would themselves come out with succour as soon as they could.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>
         With this arrangement the first party marched, about two thousand, in torrents of rain. Xenophon led his rearguard towards the visible pass, to draw the enemy’s attention and to hide the others if possible as they moved round.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
The rearguard soon reached a ravine which they must traverse before they came to the steep part; and then the barbarians rolled down round stones of all sizes, some as big as a wagon-load, which hit the rocks and splintered in all directions like slingstones—it was absolutely impossible to go near the entrance.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
Some officers baulked in this place tried others, and this went on till it was dark; when they thought they could not be seen, they went away for supper, and some of the rearguard had not even had breakfast. But the enemy did not cease rolling the stones all night, as they could hear by the noise.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         The party with the guide went round and caught the enemy outpost sitting round the fire; these they killed or chased away, and stayed there themselves, thinking they now held the height.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
But they did not hold it, for where the guards had been sitting there was a round hill above, along which ran the narrow path. However, there was an approach from this place to the enemy who were sitting on the visible road.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         Thus they spent the night; and when daylight came they formed up and moved in silence towards the enemy. There was a mist, so they were able to come near without being seen. When they caught sight of each other, the trumpet sounded, and they rushed on the fellows cheering; the enemy did not stand, but left the road and fled; few were killed, for they went light.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
Cheirisophos and his men heard the trumpet, and charged straight up by the visible road; other captains pushed along by pathless ways wherever they happened to be, getting up as they could and hoisting each other by their spears. 
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
These were the first to meet the men who had occupied the height.
         Xenophon with half the rearguard marched by the road which the party with the guide had taken, for this was quite easy for baggage-animals; the other half he posted behind the animals.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
 On the way they came to a hill above the road with enemy in possession, whom it was necessary either to cut down or else to be separated themselves from the other Hellenes. The men could have gone on above as the others had done, but the animals could not pass by any other way.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>
         Here, shouting encouragement to each other, they charged straight up the front in company columns; they did not surround it but left a way for the enemy to escape if they wished.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>
For a while the savages fought them off as well as they could, with arrows and spears, but they would not face them and ran away from the place. However, no sooner had they passed this hill than they saw another in front occupied, and determined to attack this again.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
         But Xenophon saw that if he left the captured hill, the enemy might take it again and set on the baggage-train as it passed, and the train was long in that narrow path; so he left in charge captains Cephisodoros Cephisophon’s son, an Athenian, and Amphicrates Amphidemos’ son, an Athenian, and Archagoras, an exile from Argos, and himself marched with the others to the second hill and took it in the same way. 
               </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
After this a third hill remained, the steepest of them all, the one where that outpost had been taken in the night by the volunteers.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>
But as soon as they came near, the savages left the hill without a blow, which astonished them all and made them suspect they had left it for fear of being encircled and besieged.
         But the truth was they saw from the height what was happening behind, and all moved upon the rearguard. 
               </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
      <p>
Now Xenophon with the youngest men climbed the hill, and told the others to go on, that the last companies might come up with them, until they could ground arms on the level beside the road.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
   <p>At this moment Archagoras arrived. He was in flight and said that they had been dislodged from the first hill, and that Cephisodoros and Amphicrates were dead, with all the others who had not jumped down from the rocks and got back to the rearguard.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
   <p>After this feat, the natives came to a ridge opposite to the hill, and Xenophon spoke to them through an interpreter about a truce, and asked for the dead. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
   <p>They promised to give these back on condition that they would not burn the houses. Xenophon agreed to this. While they were parleying and the rest of the army was passing, all the people of the place had been collecting; </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
   <p>and as soon as they began to descend from the hill to join the others where they were halted, the enemy charged at once in great force with loud shouts. When they were on the top of the hill which Xenophon had left, they rolled down rocks. One man’s leg was broken, and Xenophon was deserted by the man who carried his shield; </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
   <p>but Eurylochos of Lusia, one of the heavy-armed men, ran up to him and covered both with one shield, so they retreated, and the others joined the main body.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
   <p>After this, the whole Hellenic army united, and they encamped there in luxury; there were fine houses in plenty, and wine so plentiful that it was kept in cisterns of cement.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
   <p>Xenophon and Cheirisophos arranged to give up the guide in return for the dead bodies, and they rendered to the dead all the honors customary for brave men, so far as possible.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
   <p>Next day they marched without a guide; but the enemy hindered their passage by fighting and forestalling them at every narrow place. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
   <p>When they obstructed in front, Xenophon marched out from behind and made a loop over the mountains, trying to get above them and break the barrier in front; </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
   <p>when they attacked the rear, Cheirisophos marched out and tried to get above the assailants and break the barrier behind. Thus they always looked after each other and each party supported the other.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
   <p>Sometimes when a party climbed a hill for this purpose, the natives made it hot for them as they came down again, for they were so light that they could escape from quite close, as they had nothing but bows and slings. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
   <p>They were very good bowmen; they had bows of nearly three cubits, the arrows more than two cubits long. When they shot an arrow, they pressed the left foot upon the lower part of the bow as they drew the string; the arrows went through shield and corselet. When the Hellenes could get hold of any, they fitted thongs to them and used them as javelins. In these districts, the Cretans were most useful; their commander was the Cretan Stratocles.</p>
</div>
</div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">

 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         That night again they spent in the open, among the villages
         lying above the plain by the River Centritis, <note>E. Tigris</note> width
         about two hundred feet, which was the frontier between Armenia
         and the country of the Kurds. There the Hellenes
         had time to breathe, delighted to see a plain. The river was
         distant from the mountains nearly a mile.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>
There they had a
         happy night, with plenty to eat, talking and talking about
         the struggle now past. For they had spent seven days
         passing through the Kurds’ country, fighting all the time,
         and they had suffered worse things than all the king and
         Tissaphernes did to them. They were quit of all that, they
         thought, and fell happily asleep.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>At daybreak they saw horsemen somewhere across the
         river, armed and prepared to oppose a crossing, and footmen
         on the banks, marshalled above the horsemen, to hinder
         them from landing in Armenia.     </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
 These were mercenaries
         of Orontas and Artuchas, Armenian and Mardian and
         Chaldean. The Chaldeans were said to be free men and
         strong; they were armed with long wicker-work shields
         and lances.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
The banks where these ranks were standing
         were three or four furlongs away from the river; one road
         was in sight, leading upwards, apparently a regular highway.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>The Hellenes tried to cross by this road, but when
         they tried the water came over the breast, and the river-bed
         was rough with large slippery stones. They could not go
         through the water in arms, or else the river carried them
         off; they could not carry the arms on their heads, or they
         were bare against arrows and other missiles. So they retreated,
         and encamped by the riverside.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         And where they had spent the last night themselves on the mountain, they saw
         the Kurds assembled, armed, in large numbers.
         <milestone unit="para"/>Then the Hellenes were very despondent when they saw
         how difficult it was to cross the river, and when they saw
         troops ready to resist, when they saw the Kurds behind
         ready to fall on them while they crossed.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>So they stayed there in great despondency that day and
         night. But Xenophon saw a dream. He thought he was
         fastened in irons, and the fetters dropt off of themselves, so
         that he was free, and able to straddle as wide as he liked. In
         the early morning he went and told Cheirisophos that he
         had hopes all would be well, and described his dream.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>Cheirisophos was glad, and as soon as the light of dawn
         came the captains made sacrifice, all being present; and the
         omens were favourable even in the very first victim. Leaving
         the sacrifice, the captains and officers sent round word for
         the army to breakfast.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>While Xenophon sat at breakfast, two young men ran up;
         for all knew that anyone might come to him, at breakfast
         or supper, or if he slept, could awake him, and tell anything
         he had to propose for the war.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>
They told him, then, that
         they had been gathering firewood, and they saw opposite,
         among some rocks which came down to the river, an old man
         with a woman and girls laying something like bags of
         clothes in a cave in the rock. 
              </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>As they watched, they thought
         it was a safe place to cross; at least enemy horsemen could
         not come near that place. So they stript and went in naked
holding their knives, expecting to swim for it; but they
simply marched on and crossed and never wetted their
middle; then they took the clothes and came back.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>So Xenophon poured a libation at once, and told the
         young men to fill up, and to pray the gods who had shown
         the dream and the ford that they might accomplish what
         remained with good success. After this, he took the young
         men straight to Cheirisophos, and they told their story.

         
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>Cheirisophos listened, and poured a libation himself. Afterwards
         they sent round word to pack up; then called a
         meeting of the captains, and discussed how they could best
         cross and conquer those in front and not be hurt by those
         behind.
     </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>

         They decided that Cheirisophos was to lead across
with half the army, and the other half was to stay with
Xenophon, and the baggage-train to cross in the middle.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>When all was arranged they marched; the young men
         guided them, with the river on the left. It was about half
         a mile to the ford,
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
      <p> and as they marched the troops of horse
         opposite kept pace with them.
         <milestone unit="para"/>When they reached the ford and the riverbanks, they
         grounded arms; and first Cheirisophos himself put a wreath
         on his head and threw off his cloak, and took up his arms,
         giving command to the others to do the same; and he ordered
         the subalterns to lead their companions in column,
         part on his left and part on his right. Meanwhile, the soothsayers
         were sacrificing over the river.
      </p>
   </div>

   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
   <p>The enemy were shooting with bows and slings, but they were out of range.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
   <p>When the omens were favorable, all the men chanted the battle hymn and cheered, and the women all raised the woman’s hosanna of triumph, for there were many women in the camp.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
   <p>Cheirisophos then plunged in with his division; but Xenophon took the handiest men of the rearguard and doubled back to the passage on the road which led away into the Armenian mountains, pretending that he wished to cross there and cut off the horsemen along the river.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
   <p>The enemy saw Cheirisophos and his forces easily crossing the water, and Xenophon doubling back. Fearing they might be cut off, they galloped away towards the upper crossing, but as soon as they reached the road, they turned upwards towards the mountains.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
   <p>Lycios, who commanded the division of horsemen in the army of Cheirisophos, and Aischines, who commanded the light-armed troops, followed the cavalry when they saw them galloping away; and the soldiers called out, “Don’t let them get away! Follow into the mountains!”</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
   <p>Cheirisophos, when he had crossed, did not pursue the cavalry but climbed the high banks opposite the place to attack the enemy above. These, seeing their own cavalry in flight and the men-at-arms moving to attack them, abandoned the higher ground above the river.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
   <p>Xenophon, seeing that all went well across the river, doubled back towards the crossing troops, for the Kurds were visible coming down from the hills to attack the last men.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
   <p>Cheirisophos already held the upper parts, and Lycios with his little troop in pursuit caught the last of their baggage train and with it a load of fine dress and drinking cups.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
   <p>The last of the Hellenic baggage train and followers had just crossed when Xenophon returned and took a stand opposite the Kurds. He ordered the captains to form up their companies in squads and to deploy to the left in line of squads, the captains and subalterns facing the Kurds with sergeants in the rear facing the river.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
   <p>When the Kurds saw the rearguard bare of the camp followers and looking just a handful of men, they advanced more quickly, singing songs of their own. But Cheirisophos, being now in safety, sent back the light-armed troops and the bowmen and slingers to Xenophon, and told them to obey his orders.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
   <p>Xenophon saw them ready to cross; he sent a messenger with orders to stay near the river but not to go in. When he began to cross himself, they should enter the river to meet him, on the left and right, as if to cross, with javelins on the thong and arrows on the string, but they were not to go far into the river.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
   <p>To his own men the orders were: “As soon as a slingstone hits a shield and you hear the rattle, chant the battle hymn and attack the enemy. When the enemy turn and the trumpet sounds the attack, right about face and the sergeants lead, all double and each cross opposite his post so as not to interfere with each other. The first man over is the best man!”</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
   <p>The Kurds saw only a handful of men left, for many of those who had been ordered to wait were gone to look after their animals or baggage or women. At once they attacked boldly and began to sling and shoot.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31">
   <p>The Hellenes chanted their battle hymn and charged at the double, but the enemy did not wait; for they were well equipped for running up and running off in the mountains, but not for a fight hand to hand.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32">
   <p>Then the trumpet sounded the charge; the enemy ran faster than ever, and the Hellenes turned about and made for the river at full speed.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33">
   <p>Some of the enemy noticed this and ran back to the river, wounding a few with arrows, but most of them could still be seen in full flight even when the Hellenes were across.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34">
   <p>The others who came to meet them went too far in their ardor and had to cross again behind Xenophon. Some of these also were wounded.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         When they had crossed, they formed up together about midday and marched through Armenia, all plain and smooth little hills, not less than five leagues; for there were no villages near the river, because of their wars with the Kurds.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>
         But the village they reached was large and had a palace for the governor, and towers over most of the houses; provisions in abundance.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
         From there they marched two stages, 10 leagues, until they reached the source of the Tigris River. From there they marched three stages, 15 leagues, to the River Teleboas; a fine river, but not large, and there were many villages about the river.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
         This district was called Southern Armenia; the lieutenant-governor was Tiribazos, the King’s Friend, and his was the right to mount the king on horseback when he was present.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         This man rode up with a troop of horse, and sent forward an interpreter to say he wished to parley with the commanders. The captains decided to hear him, and coming within hearing, they asked what he wished.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
         He replied that he wished for a truce, on these terms: he would not damage the Hellenes, and they should not burn the houses, but take what provisions they needed. The captains agreed, and a truce was made on those terms.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         Thence they marched three stages over the plain, 15 leagues, and Tiribazos followed with his force about a mile behind. Then they reached the palace, and many villages round, full of all sorts of provisions.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
         While they were encamping, there came a heavy fall of snow; and in the morning, it was decided to billet the companies with their captains among the villages, for they saw no enemy, and it seemed to be safe with all that snow.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         There they had all the good things they wanted: sacrificial victims, corn, fragrant old wines, raisins, and all kinds of vegetables. But some stragglers from the camp reported that they had seen large numbers of fires in the night.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
         So billeting seemed no longer safe; they must assemble the army again, and so they did. The sky seemed likely to clear then, but while they slept, there came snow without end which covered the arms and the men lying there.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>
         The snow was a great hindrance to the animals, and nobody wanted to get up, for it kept them snug and warm where they lay unless it slipped off.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>
         At last Xenophon condescended to stand up in his shirt and split wood, and then one or another got up and pulled the log out of his hands and began to split; then others got up and lit fires and oiled themselves.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
         There was plenty of oil there: hog’s lard, oil from sesame and bitter almonds, and turpentine, which they used instead of olive oil. A balm also was made from the same.
      </p>
   </div>



      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
         After this, they decided to billet again under shelter. The men, with loud shouts of delight, rushed back to the shelter and provisions; and then any who had burnt the houses they left just out of mischief were sorry for it when they had bad quarters.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>
         The next night, they sent Democrates of Tenos with a few men to the mountains where stragglers said they had seen the fires; for this man had been found before to bring truthful reports, and when he said it was so, it was, and when he said it wasn’t, it was not.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
      <p>
         When he came back, he said he had seen no fires, but he brought back a prisoner armed with a Persian bow and quiver, and a bill such as the Amazons carry.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
      <p>
         Questioned, he said he was a Persian and that he was foraging for provisions from the army of Tiribazos.
         They asked how large was the army and why it had been formed.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
      <p>
He replied that Tiribazos had his own force and some mercenaries, Chalybians and Taochians; said he was prepared to fall on the Hellenes while they crossed the mountains, in narrow places with only one road.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
      <p>
         The captains decided, on hearing this, to assemble the army. They marched at once with the man as a guide, leaving guards under the command of Sophainetos, a Stymphalian.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
      <p>
         While they were crossing, the light-armed troops, going on before, caught sight of the enemy camp, and without waiting for the heavy troops, rushed on the camp with loud shouts.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
      <p>
         The natives, hearing the noise, did not stay; they ran for it. But still, some were killed, and horses were taken, about twenty, and the tent of Tiribazos was taken, and in it couches with silver feet, and cups, and men who said they were bakers and butlers.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
      <p>
         When the captains of the heavy-armed troops heard this report, they decided to return to their camp as quickly as they could to prevent an assault on those left behind. They sounded the recall and retired, and reached the camp the same day.
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
 

 <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>Next day they decided to march as quickly as possible, before the enemy could collect and occupy the narrows.
         <milestone unit="para"/>They packed up and marched at once, through deep snow, having several guides; and the same day they got over the height where Tiribazos meant to attack them, and encamped there.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>
         From that place they marched three desert stages, 15 leagues, and reached the River Euphrates, which they crossed waist-deep.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
The source was said to be not far away.
         From there they marched through deep snow over a plain, three stages, 15 leagues. The third was difficult, and a north wind blew in their faces, parching everything everywhere and freezing the men.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
         There one of the seers advised them to sacrifice to the wind, and sacrifice they did. The answer to their prayers was manifest at once to all, when the violence of the wind abated. But the snow was a fathom deep, so that many animals and slaves were lost, and soldiers too, about thirty.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         They kept fire burning all night, and so got through; there was plenty of wood in that stage, but those who came up late found none. Those who had been there long and lit the fire would not let the late ones come near the fire unless they gave them some of their wheat or anything else they had eatable.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
         Here, then, they all shared together what they had. Where the fire burned great holes were made in the snow right down to the soil, and so it was possible to measure the depth of the snow.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         The whole of the next day they were marching through snow, and many men were faint with hunger. Xenophon was in the rearguard, and he did not know what was the matter with them.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
         Someone who knew about it told him it was hunger faintness, and they would get up if he gave them something to eat; so he went round the baggage animals, and if he found food anywhere he gave it round, or sent those who could run about to give some to the sufferers.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         As soon as they had had a bite, up they got and marched on. They marched until, when darkness came, Cheirisophos reached a village and found women and girls fetching water from the fountain in front of their wall.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
         These women asked who they were. The interpreter answered in Persian that they came from the king to the governor. They said he was not there, but about one league away. Since it was late, they went together with the women to the village headman inside the stockade.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>
         Then Cheirisophos and all who could encamped there, but the rest of the army, those who could not finish the march, spent the night foodless and fireless; some of the men perished there.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>
         Parties of the enemy were always following, and carried off disabled animals and fought over them together. Men also were left behind who had been blinded by the snow or lost their toes by frostbite.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
         It did some good to the eyes if the men marched holding something black before their eyes; for the feet, to keep them moving without rest all the time and to take off the shoes at night.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
         But if any slept with shoes on, the straps worked into the feet and the shoes froze; for the old shoes were gone, and they had to make them of raw leather from untanned hides newly flayed.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>
         Through such necessities some of the soldiers were left behind, and when they saw a black patch where the snow had disappeared, they imagined that it had thawed there, and indeed it had thawed, because of a hot spring which was steaming in a dingle close by. There these men turned aside and sat, and said they would not go on.
      </p>
   </div>

   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
      <p>
         Xenophon, with some of his rearguard, noticed this, and begged them with prayers and entreaties not to stay behind, telling them that packs of the enemy were on the chase. At last, he grew angry, but they told him to cut their throats; march they could not.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
      <p>
         Then it seemed best to frighten the enemy following, if he could, and keep them off the weary men. It was dark now, and the enemy were following in confusion and quarrelling over what they had.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
      <p>
         Then the rearguard, who were well and strong enough, jumped up and ran for the enemy, and the weary men shouted as loud as they could and banged spears against their shields. The enemy were frightened and smashed through the snow into the dingle, and not a sound was heard from them again.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
      <p>
         Xenophon and his party told the weary men that someone would come for them tomorrow and marched on. They had not gone half a mile when they came on their soldiers on the road, lying upon the snow wrapped up and trying to sleep, without any guard at all, and he made them get up.
         They said those in front would not go on.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
      <p>
He passed by and sent on the strongest of his light troops to see what was in the way. They reported that the whole army was sleeping like that.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
      <p>
         Then Xenophon settled down there for the night, without fire or food, after posting such guards as he could. When day was near, Xenophon sent the youngest of his men back to the weary men, with orders to make them get up and force them to march.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
      <p>
         Meanwhile, Cheirisophos sent men from the village to see how the rear was doing. Glad indeed they were to see them and handed over the weary men to be taken to the camp, while they marched themselves, and two or three miles farther on they reached the village where Cheirisophos had spent the night.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
      <p>
         When they met, they thought it was safe to billet the companies in the villages. Cheirisophos remained where he was, and the others drew lots for the villages in sight, and each led his men to their place.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
      <p>
         Now Polycrates, an Athenian officer, asked for special leave, and taking the most active of his men, he ran to the village allotted to Xenophon, and found all the villagers inside, and their headman, and colts which were being reared for the king’s tribute, seventeen, and the headman’s daughter nine days wedded; her husband was out hunting hares, and he was not caught in the village.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
      <p>
         The houses were underground, the mouth like a well, roomy underneath; the people went down by ladders, but the animals had a way dug for them. In the houses were sheep, goats, cattle, birds, and their young; all the beasts were fed indoors on green stuff.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
      <p>
         There was also wheat and barley and vegetables, and barley wine in tubs; there were barley grains floating on the wine at the rim, and straws lay there, large and small, without knots.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
      <p>
         If you were thirsty, you picked up one of these and sucked through it. It was very strong wine if drunk neat, and the taste was delicious when you were used to it.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
      <p>
         Xenophon made the headman of this village share his table, and told him to fear nothing; they would not rob him of his children, but they would fill the house with provisions before they went if he would do good service to the army and guide them to some other tribe.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
      <p>
         The man promised, and with all goodwill showed him where the wine was buried. That night, billeted thus, all the soldiers rested in the midst of abundance, keeping the headman under guard and his family with him safe in sight.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
      <p>
         On the next day, Xenophon took the headman before Cheirisophos. Whenever he passed a village, he looked in and found them everywhere feasting and making merry. The people never let them go without offering breakfast.
      </p>
   </div>




      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31">
      <p>
         Everywhere on the same table were piles of lamb, kid, pork, veal, fowl, with all sorts of cakes, both wheaten and barley.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32">
      <p>
When one would show goodwill by drinking your health, he dragged you to the bowl, and you must duck your head and gulp it up like a bullock. They let the headman take away whatever he liked. But he would accept nothing, only if he saw any of his own kinsmen, he took him away with him.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>When they reached Cheirisophos, they found them there in their quarters, garlanded with hay and served by Armenian boys in their native costume; they made signs to the boys as if they were deaf and dumb to show what they wanted.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34">
      <p>
 After Cheirisophos and Xenophon had greeted one another affectionately, they asked the headman together through the interpreter who spoke Persian, “What country is this?” He said, “Armenia.” They asked again for whom he was breeding the colts. He said, “Tribute for the king.”
          The neighbouring country, he said, was the Chalybeans, <pb n="101"/>and pointed where the road was. 
               </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35">
      <p>
Then Xenophon led him to his own servants, and gave him an oldish horse which he had caught to feed up and sacrifice, because he heard that the horse was sacred to the Sun<note>This was an Indian custom; a horse was consecrated and let loose.</note>: he was afraid it might die, for it had suffered from the march. He took one of the colts himself, and gave a colt each to the other captains and officers.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36">
      <p>
         The horses in this place were smaller than the Persian, but much more spirited. Then the headman taught him to wrap bags round the feet of the baggage-horses when they are driven through snow; without the bags, they sink down to the belly.
      </p>
   </div>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>When the eighth day came, he gave the headman as guide to Cheirisophos, but left all the headman’s household except his son, just growing up; this boy he entrusted to Pleisthenes of Amphipolis, and he should be given back if the man was a good guide. They filled his house with all the supplies they could find and marched away.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>
         The headman guided them through the snow; the third stage came, and still there were no villages, which made Cheirisophos very angry. The man said there were no villages in that part.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
Cheirisophos then struck him, but he did not bind him, and in consequence that night he deserted and left his son.
         This was the only difference between Xenophon and Cheirisophos in the whole march: the violence done to the guide and the carelessness. <milestone unit="para"/>Pleisthenes fell in love with the boy, and brought him home, and found him most faithful.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
         After this they marched seven stages at five leagues a day to the River Phasis, width two feet.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         Thence they marched two stages, 10 leagues, and in the descent they were met by Chalybeans, Taothans, and Phasians.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
         When Cheirisophos caught sight of the enemy at the pass, he halted about three miles away, that he might not approach the enemy marching in column. He sent orders round to form line of companies in column.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         When the rearguard came up, he summoned captains and officers and said: “The enemy, as it appears, hold the pass, and we must consider how best to fight.       </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
I think it best to order the men to breakfast, and then we should deliberate whether to cross today or tomorrow.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         Cleanor said, “My opinion is that when we have breakfasted, we should arm at once and attack. If we delay today, the present enemy will be bolder, and it is likely that many others will join them while they are confident.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
         Xenophon spoke: “My opinion is this. If a fight cannot be avoided, we ought to be ready to fight our strongest. But if we wish to traverse the pass most easily, we should consider how to pass with fewest wounds and smallest loss of men."
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>
         "What we see of the mountain is seven or eight miles across, and the men waiting for us are visible only on the road; it is much better, then, to try to steal some part of the empty space and get round unseen, if we can, than to attack fortifications and men prepared to fight."
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>
         "For it is much easier to climb a steep place without fighting than to go along the flat with enemies on each side; without fighting we can see better at night what is in front of our feet than we can by day while fighting; and the rough way before our feet will be easier to tread without fighting than the level path when our heads are being battered."
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
         "To steal a march does not seem impossible to me, since we can go by night so as not to be seen, and keep far enough away so as not to be heard; and if we make a feint of attacking here the mountain will be more deserted, since the enemy would remain all together where they are."
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
         "But why do I give my notions about stealing? You Lacedaimonians, as I hear, Cheirisophos, you who belong to the Spartan peers, practise the art of stealing from boyhood; it is not base to steal, but honourable, where the law does not forbid."
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>
         "But to steal cleverly and not to be caught, that is lawful surely, I think, and to be thrashed if you are caught stealing. Then now’s the time to show off your education, and take care not to be caught stealing a bit of the hill and not to be thrashed.”
      </p>
   </div>



      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
      <p>
         “Well indeed,” said Cheirisophos, “I hear you Athenians are clever at stealing public funds, although there is terrible risk for the thief, and your biggest men are the biggest thieves, if the biggest men are honoured with high office! Then just show off your own education!”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
      <p>
         “All right,” said Xenophon, “I’m ready! After supper I'll take the rearguard and go and capture the mountain. I have my guides; for the light-armed among my attendant thieves have caught some by lying in wait. I hear from them that the mountain is not impassable, but goats and cattle feed there; so if we can once get a bit of mountain, our baggage-animals can go too. 
               </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
      <p>
And I expect the enemy won’t stay here themselves, when they see us on the heights like them; even now they will not come down to meet us on equal terms.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
      <p>
         Cheirisophos said, “And why should you go and leave your rearguard? Just tell others to go, if no good volunteers turn up.”
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
      <p>
         Then Aristonymos the Methydrian came with men-at-arms, and Aristeas the Chian with light troops, and Nicomachos the Oitaian with light troops, and they arranged to kindle plenty of fires when they held the heights.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>With this arrangement they took breakfast; and after that Cheirisophos led the army about a mile towards the enemy, to make them believe that the attack would come there.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
      <p>
         <milestone unit="para"/>After supper, when night came, the men told off went and got possession of the mountain, and the others rested where they were. When the enemy had news that the mountain was held, they awoke and lit many fires through the night.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
      <p>
         At daybreak Cheirisophos sacrificed and led along the road, those who held the mountain advanced along the heights, 
               </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
      <p>
and most of the enemy remained at the pass, but a detachment went to meet those on the mountain.
         Before the main bodies came together, the two parties on the heights met, the Hellenes conquered and gave chase.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
      <p>
Meanwhile on the plain the light-armed Hellenes went at the double towards the ranks of the enemy, and Cheirisophos followed with the heavy troops at quick march.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
      <p>
         The enemy on the road took to flight as soon as they saw the others worsted on the hills. Not many of them were killed, but they left large quantities of wicker shields, which the Hellenes chopt up with their swords and made useless. 
              </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
      <p>
When all had come up they sacrificed and set up a trophy, and then descended into the plain, where they found villages full of good things.
      </p>
   </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
      <p>
         After this, they marched into the Taochian country, five stages, 30 leagues. Provisions now failed them; for the Taochians lived in strong places where they had carried up all their stores.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
      <p>
The army reached a stronghold, not a city, without houses, but full of gathered men, women, and flocks. Cheirisophos immediately attacked; battalion after battalion went forward and failed, for the place could not be surrounded due to the steep slopes.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
      <p>
When Xenophon arrived with the rearguard and both light and heavy troops, Cheirisophos said: 
 
          "Just in time. This place must be taken, or the army will have no food."
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
      <p>
         They consulted. "Why don’t you just walk in?" asked Xenophon.

         Cheirisophos answered, "There’s only one way in, as you see. Whenever we try to go, they roll stones down from that projecting rock. If someone’s caught, see what happens," and he pointed to shattered men with broken legs and ribs.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
      <p>
         "If they use up their stones," said Xenophon, "there will be nothing stopping us. All I see are a few men, only two or three armed.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
      <p>
The distance to cross exposed is hardly fifty yards. There are groves of pines ahead; if men shelter behind them, they won’t be harmed by stones. The final few yards can be rushed when the stones slacken."
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
      <p>
         "Oh yes," said Cheirisophos, "but as soon as we approach, down come the stones!" 

         "Exactly," Xenophon replied. "They’ll use up their stones faster. Let’s approach and leave only a short dash to run if we must retreat."
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
      <p>
         Cheirisophos, Xenophon, and Callimachos the Parrhasian—a rear officer for the day—moved forward while others stayed behind. Under the trees, about seventy men advanced cautiously, one by one, each guarding himself. 
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
      <p>
         Outside the trees, Agasias the Stymphalian and Aristonymos the Methydrian, along with others, stood watch. The trees provided cover, but only one company could stand safely at a time. 
         
              </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
      <p>
Callimachos devised a plan: he stepped out briefly and retreated as stones flew, causing the defenders to waste their ammunition. 
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
      <p>
         Seeing this, Agasias, eager to be first into the stronghold, ran forward without calling anyone.      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
      <p>
Callimachos caught his shield rim as Aristonymos raced past them, followed by Eurylochos. Competing for valor, they stormed the position. No stones came after them once they entered.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
      <p>
         The sight inside was dreadful. Women threw their children down the cliffs and leapt after them, as did the men. Aineias, a Stymphalian officer, tried to save a man in fine clothes      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
      <p>
but was dragged down with him. Both perished. Few people survived, but the Greeks captured many cattle, donkeys, and sheep.
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
      <p>
         From there, they marched through Chalybean territory, seven stages, 50 leagues. These were the toughest foes they encountered, ready for hand-to-hand combat, wearing linen corselets to the groin with thick ropes instead of leather wings.
      </p>
   </div>

   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
   <p>
      <milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>They had greaves also and helmets and by the belt a knife as long as a Laconian dagger. They used it to slaughter those they could capture, cutting off the heads and carrying them away. They would sing and dance whenever they expected the enemy to see them. They also carried spears about fifteen cubits long with a single spike.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
   <p>They kept to their fortified places, and as the Hellenes passed, they followed always fighting. Their provisions were stored in their fortresses, so the Hellenes got nothing from the Chalybean lands but subsisted on the cattle and sheep taken from the Taochians.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
   <p>From there, the Hellenes came to the Harpasos River, four plethra wide. From there they traveled through Scythenians, four stages, twenty leagues, crossing a plain to villages. They stayed three days, gathering supplies.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
   <p>From these villages, they traveled four stages, twenty leagues, reaching a large, prosperous, and inhabited city called Gymnias. The local ruler sent a guide to lead them through the hostile lands.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
   <p>When the guide arrived, he told them he would lead them within five days to a place where they could see the sea. If not, he offered his life as forfeit. Upon entering the hostile region, he urged them to burn and destroy it, revealing his intention was revenge, not friendship toward the Hellenes.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
   <p>They reached the mountain on the fifth day; its name was Theches. When the vanguard reached the summit and saw the sea, a great shout arose.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
   <p>Hearing the shouts, Xenophon and the rearguard thought enemies were attacking the front. Pursuers had been following from the burning countryside, and the rearguard had killed some, captured others, and taken about twenty wicker shields covered with raw oxhides.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
   <p>But as the shouts grew louder, and more men rushed forward, it became evident that something greater was happening. Xenophon, realizing it might be significant, mounted his horse and rode ahead with Lycios and the cavalry.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
   <p>They soon heard the soldiers shouting "Thalatta! Thalatta!" (The sea! The sea!) and passing the word along. Then everyone ran, including the rearguard and even the baggage animals.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
   <p>When they all reached the summit, they embraced one another, officers and men alike, with tears streaming. Suddenly someone gave an order, and the soldiers began gathering stones, building a great mound.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
   <p>There they placed the raw oxhides, staffs, and the captured shields. The guide himself cut up the shields and encouraged the others to do the same.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
   <p>The Hellenes then dismissed the guide with gifts from the common treasury: a horse, a silver bowl, Persian dress, and ten darics. He asked particularly for rings and received many from the soldiers. Pointing out a village for their encampment and the route to the Macrones, he departed during the night.
   </p>
</div>
</div>

</div>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>